<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The court of St. Germain's: or, The secret history of the late King James and Queen Mary From their first arrival in France, to this time. From the French original.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1695</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 166 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 75 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A80694</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C6591A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R224546</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99896959</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99896959</idno>
            <idno type="VID">135703</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A80694)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 135703)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2463:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The court of St. Germain's: or, The secret history of the late King James and Queen Mary From their first arrival in France, to this time. From the French original.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>144 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>printed in the year, MDCXCV. [1695]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library, Washington, D.C.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>James --  II, --  King of England, 1633-1701 --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Kings and rulers --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:135703:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:135703:1"/>
            <p>THE COURT OF St. <hi>GERMAIN</hi>'s: OR, THE Secret Hiſtory OF The Late King <hi>JAMES</hi> and Queen <hi>MARY.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From Their Firſt Arrival in <hi>France,</hi> to this Time.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>From the</hi> French <hi>Original.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year, MDCXCV.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:135703:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:135703:2"/>
            <head>THE COURT OF St. <hi>GERMAINS.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THEIR <hi>Britannic</hi> Majeſties had no ſooner quitted <hi>London,</hi> and diſpoſſeſſed themſelves of Three Kingdoms, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ey were received at <hi>Paris</hi> by all the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ourt. Where the <hi>French</hi> King, to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſſen their Sorrows, endeavoured by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the moſt engaging ways in the World, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> aſſwage their Grief, which their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ration from Enthronement might oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſion; and to that effect, after he had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ven K. <hi>James,</hi> and the Queen his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rt, all the Demonſtrations of Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:135703:3"/>Friendſhip, accompany'd with an Extraordinary Generoſity, 'twas His Majeſties Pleaſure to make 'em partak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of all the Pleaſures and moſt Charm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Paſtimes of his Court. Among the reſt our Monarch propos'd to the Q. now fled to him for Succour, the Divertiſements of Amorous Courtſhip and other Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creations, as the moſt acceptable means to allay the Anguiſh of her Troubles. Nor did the Queen, who had always an inclination leaning that way, make any great Reſiſtance; which extreamly pleaſed the King, who was not altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther inſenſible of a growing Kindneſs for her, and who had given her certain proofs of it ſince her arrival in <hi>France.</hi> Some time after their Abode at St. <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains,</hi> which is the place of their Reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, the King ordered the Archbiſhop of <hi>Paris,</hi> and the Biſhop of <hi>Meaux</hi> to viſit their Majeſties, and to infuſe into 'em that Patience which was neceſſary for good Catholicks. And that Illuſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Prelate employed a World of Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence to make it out to the King and Queen from Examples in Hiſtory, that they were not the only Princes who had loſt their Crowns, and that it was a glorious thing to ſuffer the Croſſes and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:135703:3"/>Afflictions of this Life with Conſtancy, and without Murmuring. Which done he took his leave, deeply ſmitt'n with the Merits of that Princeſs who had made appear ſo much Solidity in all her Diſcourſe, and convinced him that the Court of <hi>France</hi> was not the only place that monopolized all that was worthy of Eſteem and Love.</p>
            <p>It may be therefore ſaid, That from that very Day the Queen knew how to manage her Conqueſt, and preſerve it: And in regard ſhe is an <hi>Italian,</hi> as being the Duke of <hi>Modena</hi>'s Daughter, and nearly related to the Pope, ſhe carry'd her ſelf with a great deal of Addreſs and Artifice. Nor would the Reverend Fathers the Jeſuits be ſilent upon ſuch an occaſion as this; every one would go to pay their Reſpects to their Majeſties, more eſpecially the Fathers <hi>La Chaiſe</hi> and <hi>Bourdalou</hi> made it a conſiderable part of their buſineſs, as they that took great delight to report their Obſervations to the King. And indeed the frequent Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſits of our Monarch, the Dauphin, and all the Ladies, cauſed the Queen to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get a good part of her Sorrows. The Princes of <hi>Conti,</hi> and <hi>Eſpinoi</hi> propound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to her Hunting Matches with the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:135703:4"/>Dutcheſs of <hi>Orleans,</hi> who prefers Hunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing before all other Sports in the World, as being frequently at the Head of the Hounds, Apparell'd like the reſt of the Huntſmen.</p>
            <p>At St. <hi>Clou</hi>'s it was, where firſt they taſted thoſe Country Pleaſures, which were attended with a Ball, and a magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficent Banquet, the Violins and Haut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boys playing all the Night. The Fair Ladies who were the Ornament of that Feſtival, appear'd in all their Splendor. More particularly the Counteſs <hi>de Rourre</hi> diſplay'd all her Excellencies in that Charming Aſſembly, and in regard ſhe is none of the moſt Accompliſh'd Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, ſhe made the beſt of her pleaſant Humour, much more amiable than her Features. The Danphin, who has more than ordinary kindneſs for her, never left her, and gave her to underſtand by many pretty Amorous Intimations, how much he Lov'd her; but the Princeſs of <hi>Liſlebonne,</hi> and the Marchioneſs of <hi>Segna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay,</hi> who had a watchful Eye upon 'em, ever and anon would needs be interrupt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Monſieurs tender and paſſionate Expreſſions, which very much diſguſted <hi>Madam de Rourre;</hi> inſomuch that ſhe made her Complaint to the Princeſs of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:135703:4"/>
               <hi>Conti,</hi> who is the Duphin's Confident, telling her, That ſhe was very Unfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate to be ſo narrowly obſerved, even to the ſlighteſt of her Actions, which cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the Princeſs to Laugh, who in that merry fit went immediately and made the King acquainted with the Counteſs's Grievances. The King made himſelf ſport with it, and becauſe they thought the Dauphin far remote from any Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Engagement, they forbore to watch him ſo narrowly; wherein the Court was deceived; for they found by the ſequel, that the young Prince was as ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of Love as other Men; which we ſhall indeavour to ſhew in the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Relations.</p>
            <p>Let us return to the Queen, whom our Arcbiſhop had not the power to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake, without ſpeaking of that Love which reign'd ſo predominantly in his Heart. But in regard that Prelates have not the Liberty which others have to expreſs their Amorous Thougths, the Archbiſhop was contented with enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Preſence of her who had wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his Heart: Only Sighs and Languiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Looks were the Faithful Interpreters of his Paſſion, while he ſtill obſerved
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:135703:5"/>thoſe meaſures that ſuited beſt with his Character.</p>
            <p>But the Queen, who is expert in the Affair of Gallantry, ſoon Divin'd the meaning of his mute Language, as ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving an Inclination ſufficiently prone to embrace the Sanctify'd Love of Men of the Church, which encloſes within it unknown Myſteries. She had not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got the ſweet Hours ſhe had paſt away with her dear Nuncio <hi>Dada,</hi> whom the Pope had ſent into <hi>England,</hi> to manage his Intereſts. For which reaſon it was, that ſhe gladly and joyfully admitted Monſieur the Archbiſhop's Viſits, and went oftner in her Coach to hear Maſs and Veſpers in the Convent of the <hi>Auſtin</hi>-Fryars, attended by her Confident the Marchioneſs of <hi>P—s.</hi> Love and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion were in her inſeparable, through a Secret Union; which uſually happens in <hi>Italy,</hi> where the Churches are the pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of meeting for the carrying on of Love Intrigues. The Reſpect our Prelate had for a Princeſs ſo haughty and ſo handſome reſtrain'd him from telling her what he felt for her ſake. But when he bethought himſelf that a Perſon of his Character had been belov'd, thoſe Idea's fortify'd her Hopes, and rendered him
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:135703:5"/>more undaunted in his Enterprize. On the other ſide the change of her For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, and the Paſſion which a certain <hi>Engliſh</hi> Lord has for that Charming Princeſs, and her Courtly manner of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering his Careſſes, perſwaded the Archbiſhop that he had not long to ſigh in vain. So that at laſt the happy Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nute arrived, and the Archbiſhop made known his Tender Sentiments to his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine <hi>Queen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>One Day that King <hi>James</hi> was at <hi>Marly,</hi> with the Duke of <hi>Vendoſme,</hi> Grand Prior of <hi>France,</hi> the Count of St. <hi>Maure,</hi> and ſeveral Lords of the Court, the Archbiſhop, whom the Qu. had made acquainted with it in the Morning, giving him withal to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, with a Graceful Aire, That ſhe ſhould be glad of his Company in the Afternoon, being all alone at St. <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main</hi>'s, our Archbiſhop, I ſay, upon theſe Encouragements, let her ſee by a profound Obeyſance and a low Bow, that his Heart was brim-full of Joy, and that he would not fail to make the beſt of his Opportunity. To which pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe he ordered his Lacqueys to change their Liveries, and being himſelf muf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fled up in a Scarlet Cloak, that he might
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:135703:6"/>in ſome meaſure diſguiſe himſelf, and deceive the People, who will always be pratling, eſpecially at <hi>Paris,</hi> he entered the Caſtle, and meeting the Marchioneſs of <hi>P—s,</hi> who was in the Anti-Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber with one of the Queens Maids of Honour, he gave her a Smile, as he gently puſh'd open the Door of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>binet, where our Princeſs ſate Reading the Amours of <hi>Henry</hi> IV. very much wond<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing at his Inconſtancy, and the number of his Miſtreſſes, which made her Laugh, when ſhe began to conſider how little reaſon Ladies had to rely up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Paſſion and Affections of Men. Monſieur, the Archbiſhop, after he had Saluted the Queen, opened his Heart, and gave her to underſtand ſome part of his pains. To which the Princeſs, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding him with a tender Look, made anſwer, That ſhe would ſee what might be done to render him leſs unhappy. Our Prelate ſeemed to be raviſhed with the Charms of her ſoft Expreſſions, and preſently throwing himſelf at her Feet, embrac'd her knees, and kiſſing her hands a thouſand times, proteſted to her that he never was ſo deeply in Love in his Life before. Then they laid their Heads together to conſider which way they
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:135703:6"/>might fee one another, without being diſcovered by the Court. But it was a difficult matter to deceive the Hundred-Ey'd <hi>Argus</hi>'s which our Monarch has prying about in all parts, to the end that nothing may eſcape him that is tranſacted in the City. At length the Queen told her new Lover, after ſhe had pondered a while, That it would be the beſt way for him to diſguiſe himſelf ſometimes like a Muſick Maſter, for that ſhe being a paſſionate Lover of Muſick, neither the King her Husband, nor any body elſe would take any notice of him; or elſe like a Bookſeller that brought her Novels and Hiſtories to read. This pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſal was well approved; but the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion was, How to carry the Buſineſs neatly. To which purpoſe every thing was juſt concluded upon, when a Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman brought the Queen Letters from the Counteſs of <hi>Tyrconnel,</hi> who had been one of her Maids of Honour, and whom the King had Marry'd to his Deputy of <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Queen was overjoy'd to hear Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings from her dear Friend, who had ſerv'd her in ſeveral perilous occaſions, no leſs ſorry that ſhe had her not then with her to aſſiſt her in the preſent Intrigue,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:135703:7"/>being well aſſured, That that ſame Lady would have been a great help to her, as being one that perfectly knew how to counterfeit Devotion, and talked of nothing elſe but the Holy Fathers of the Church, and of their Sufferings. King <hi>James</hi> being returned from <hi>Marly,</hi> took great delight in giving the Queen an Account of the Paſtime he had taken in that little Journey, and how kindly he had been entertain'd by the Duke of <hi>Vendoſme</hi> and the Count of St. <hi>Maure.</hi> The good Prince related every Paſſage with the greateſt Candor and Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom in the World, never dreaming of the Amorous Commerce of his tender Conſort, who every way endeavoured to fulfil the King her Husband's Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie.</p>
            <p>For one Morning that K. <hi>James,</hi> then only Duke of <hi>York,</hi> and a Widower, was walking in the Long-Gallery next to St. <hi>James</hi>'s-<hi>Park,</hi> with ſome others of the Nobility: it ſo fell out that he met with an Aſtrologer in that place. The Duke of <hi>York</hi> perceiving a great Throng of People-gathered together, and curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to know the reaſon of the noiſe they made, went up directly to the Crowd with his Company, and asked,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:135703:7"/>What the matter was? At what time a Gentleman told him, That they had got among 'em a Famous Aſtrologer, who ſaw in the Face of any man what would befal him in his Life time. This created in the Duke a deſire to know his own Deſtiny, ſo that he commanded the Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard to attend him after Dinner, which the Old South-ſayer did. He excuſed himſelf however as long as he could, alledging the danger of telling Princes and Princeſſes their Fortunes, for that being expoſed to the Capricio's of For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune as well as other Men, the Truth was not many times to be ſpoken.</p>
            <p>But the unwillingneſs of the Aſtrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger encreaſing the Duke of <hi>York</hi>'s deſire, he preſt the Artiſt ſo much the more earneſtly, and giving him his Hand told him withal, <hi>That whatever the Planets had appointed for him, he would take it in good part.</hi> Then the Aſtrologer looking ſtedfaſtly in the Duke's Face, uttered this Oracle, <hi>That if there were any Truth in the Stars, he would be in danger of</hi> Acte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on<hi>'s Fate, whenever he ſhould chance to ſee a</hi> Diana <hi>Naked in the Bath.</hi> Upon which all the Nobility that were preſent fell a Laughing, and a long time after in their
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:135703:8"/>Merriments made Sport with the Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loger and his Prediction. Some Years after this, when the thing was in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner forgot, the D. of <hi>York</hi> went to the Bath, either for his Health, or for his Pleaſure, and there, never dreaming of the Propheſie, by an Accident beheld a Lovely Young Lady, and of great Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, Naked in one of the Baths, who Chid him for not withdrawing from the place, conſidering the Condition ſhe was in. So that the ſatisfaction which the Duke had in ſtaring upon a Beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and Charming Lady in the State of Innocence, concurr'd to make out the truth of an Unlucky Prediction.</p>
            <p>Let us now leave K. <hi>James</hi> II. to bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zon his new Coat of Arms, and let us endeavour to ſhew how it was enlarg'd and beautify'd by the number of his Dear Conſorts Favourites. Monſieur the Arcbiſhop having upon a St. <hi>John</hi>'s Day caſt ſeveral paſſionate Looks upon the Queen in the Church, which were obſerv'd by the Dauphin and the Duke of <hi>Vendoſm</hi> his Minion, thoſe two No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Perſonages, ſo ſoon as Sermon was done, went to walk in the <hi>Louvre,</hi> Laughing all the while at the Prelates Amours. <hi>A very fine Buſineſs,</hi> cry'd
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:135703:8"/>the Dauphin, <hi>You ſee the Eccleſiaſticks are ſubject to the ſame Temptations as we are our ſelves. I remember I have heard it ſaid at Court, that the Abbot of</hi> Bois Robert <hi>ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with Cardinal</hi> Mazarine, <hi>who was a Man of a wonderful Devotion, the Favours of the Beautiful</hi> Marion de l'Orme. <hi>By my Faith,</hi> reply'd the Duke ſmiling, <hi>ſince you aſſure me 'tis ſo, I'll try to be our Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop's Rival: We are good Friends enough to have one Miſtreſs between us. Go on,</hi> ſaid the Dauphin to the Duke, clapping him upon the Shoulder, <hi>go and puſh on your Good Fortune, if the Conqueſt pleaſes you.</hi> This Diſcourſe would have laſted longer, but the vaſt number of People that meet in the <hi>Louvre,</hi> cauſed our two Sparks to take Coach again, and drive from thence to the Princeſs of <hi>Turennes,</hi> whom they found walking in one of the Alleys in her Garden. So ſoon as the Dauphin ſaw her, <hi>What, Madam,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>taking the freſh Air all alone?— Yes, Sir,</hi> anſwer'd ſhe, <hi>I came out of my Cabinet to divert my Melancholy. What is the cauſe of your Diſquiet, Madam, that makes you ſo Contemplative,</hi> reply'd the Dauphin, <hi>if we may be permitted to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire. Oh, Sir,</hi> — reply'd the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, <hi>the Inſenſibility of your Heart will not
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:135703:9"/>give you leave to underſtand it.</hi> Monſieur would have unfolded his Sentiments to the Princeſs of <hi>Turenne,</hi> when the Count of St. <hi>Maure</hi> entered the Garden, who propoſed a Game at Cards, which took up the reſt of the Day very pleaſantly; only the Princeſs could not be reconcil'd to her ſelf for having gone ſo far in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcovering her tender Affection for the Dauphin, who ſo ill requited it. He was ſo taken up with the Favours Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam <hi>de Rourre</hi> beſtowed upon him, and whom he ſincerely Loved even before ſhe was Marry'd, when ſhe was only one of the Dauphineſſes Maids of Honour, that he very little minded the Careſſes of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mademoiſelle de la Force,</hi> now <hi>Made<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moiſelle de Rourre,</hi> was always ſo full of her Wanton Tricks, and ſuch a Coc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet with all, that every time ſhe ſaw the Monſieur, if he were not in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany with the Dauphineſs, that Incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable Lady had ſtill ſomething to ſay to the Dauphin ſo divertiſing, that ſhe made him Laugh. For which reaſon it was that the Court gave her the Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thite of the <hi>Witty Jeſter.</hi> But this Gay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety included within it an Ambitious de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign: For it was to enſnare the Dau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phin's
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:135703:9"/>Heart that the young Artiſt laid her Springes; wherein ſhe has ſucceeded to a Miracle; ſince tis certain that the Illuſtrious Dauphin has ſmitten her in the moſt ſenſible part.</p>
            <p>But to return to the Princeſs of <hi>Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renne,</hi> ſhe had taken another way to ſtop the Career of the Prince's Affection. She had ſhewed him the ſtrength of her firſt Paſſion, in telling him, That her Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe depended upon an Auſpicious Glance, an endearing caſt of his Eyes, to which the Monſieur did not anſwer like a Graceful Courtier, which drew upon him the Raillery of ſome Unlucky Lampoons.</p>
            <p>The Prince of <hi>Turenne</hi> deſirous of a ſecret Revenge, had offered his Vows to the Counteſs of <hi>Bourre,</hi> who had allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed 'em a favourable Reception, which extreamly perplexed the Count her Husband, who was a Good Man, that could have loved an Honeſt Woman. I muſt leave the reſt for a while, to find out our <hi>Sorbonne</hi> Doctor, who was buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly employ'd in compoſing a Letter as tender as his Heart, to be ſent to the Queen at St. <hi>Germains,</hi> whom he had not ſeen ſince the Day before. We im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:135703:10"/>it to the Reader as it came to o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Hands.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>A Letter of Monſieur the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop to the Q<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>EEN.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Madam,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>THoſe Hours which I waſte remote fro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> your Company, ſeem to me of an infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite length. It would be my greateſt plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, <hi>Divine Queen,</hi> to aſſure you, ever<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> minute, of my Love, and of the ſtrength <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> my Paſſion. Oh! What a Life ſhould <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> lead, could my Good Fortune but procure <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſo great a Felicity! But I was not Born <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> taſte ſo Heavenly a Happineſs. I muſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore be contented with the favour which I en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy by your Permiſſion, which is to taſte th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Fruition of your Adorable Preſence, as op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity will give me leave. Adien <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> I will wait upon you this After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noon.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Our Prelate ſent this Letter to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Queen by one of his Lacqueys, whom he ordered to change his Livery, and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:135703:10"/>put on the Marchioneſs of <hi>Signalay</hi>'s Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours, who frequently viſited the Queen, and ſent her little Preſents almoſt every Day. And the new Lover of an Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop followed the Lacquey almoſt at the Heels.</p>
            <p>Monſieur the Archbiſhop had for that Day laid aſide his Gravity and his Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifical Habits to Apparel himſelf like a Bookſeller that furniſhed the Queen with new Books. No Man in the World could have better diſguiſed himſelf then our Doctor of the <hi>Sorbonne.</hi> Mrs. <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bady</hi> who is one of the Queens Women, knew him not in that Disfigurement, but carry'd him into her Miſtreſſes Cabinet, without any Ceremony. Nor did the Queen give him any other than a cold Reception in her riſing up to Salute him. Whither it were that the Prelate did not pleaſe her in that ſame Dreſs of a Citizen, or that the News which ſhe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived every Day from <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> where Affairs went no way to her ſatisfaction, had put her into an ill Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, or whither it were that the laſt Viſits of this ſame Gallant, with his Spectacles upon his Noſe, had cool'd her Ardour, not finding in him the Brisk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of a Youthful Champion, nor the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:135703:11"/>Charming Vigour of her <hi>Adonis Dada</hi> In ſhort our Adorable <hi>Venus</hi> could not endure the Amorous Careſſe of the <hi>Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bonne</hi> Doctor, without ſome kind of Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſineſs, which was a great trouble to<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> him, and forced him to ask her the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> cauſe of her coldneſs. <hi>Ah, Madam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> cry'd the Prelate all inflamed, <hi>I Lov<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> you to that degree that never Woman wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> more beloved, Wherefore do you not anſwe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Violence of my Paſſion?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Queen who ſaw that her Reluct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ancy had warmed the Heart and Impagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of her Lover, and that he began to be impatient, granted what he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, moſt tenderly embracing him Which overjoy'd the <hi>Roman Patriarch,</hi> ſo that he Kiſs'd his Lovely Goddeſs a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thouſand times as ſhe ſate upon his knee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Thus Charm'd with his Good Fortune, at length he took his leave of the <hi>Queen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> hearing that <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. was coming to give her a Viſit. <hi>Alas!</hi> (ſaid he in a great Fume) <hi>What a World of Meaſure are we bound to obſerve? My Misfortune re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duces me to keep fair with a World of People for whom</hi> I <hi>have no kindneſs! Strange for of Politicks! Now St.</hi> Mary <hi>of</hi> Lorette<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>have pity upon me.</hi> The Queen was alſo making her Devout Lamentations, when
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:135703:11"/>the K. ſurpriz'd her, and ask'd her with whom ſhe was talking ſo dolefully. <hi>Sir,</hi> ſaid ſhe, I <hi>was praying to our good Saint of</hi> Loretto <hi>that ſhe would vouchſafe to reſtore me to my Throne. Oh, Madam,</hi> reply'd his Majeſty, drawing his Sword, <hi>this ſame Steel ſhall revenge your Cauſe in due time.</hi> The Queen ſeemed ſurpriz'd and admiring the King's Valour, <hi>Sir,</hi> ſaid ſhe, with a ſmile, <hi>put up your Sword a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the time of Battle;</hi> which the <hi>Hector</hi> of <hi>Tory</hi> did accordingly.</p>
            <p>The Queen who was tyr'd out with the Complacency which ſhe had been forced to ſhew the Archbiſhop held no long Diſcourſe with our Monarch, who could not divine the reaſon of his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſes unequal Temper. As for the <hi>Roman</hi> Doctor who was gone to one of his Friends Houſes to ſhift himſelf, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eaſſume his Sacerdotal Veſtments, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ore he could return to his Palace, he was much troubled when he underſtood by Mr. <hi>Vincent</hi> his <hi>Valet de Chambre,</hi> that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e had been ſtay'd for all the Day at the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>orbonne</hi> about Buſineſs relating to the <hi>Church,</hi> and that the Biſhop of <hi>Meaux</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ad been ſeeking for him up and down <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>om place to place to ſpeak with him.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:135703:12"/>
            <p>Aboutthe ſame time the Duke of <hi>Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doſme,</hi> who had told the Dauphin in Merriment, that he intended to be the Archbiſhop's Rival, went to St. <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains</hi> with a deſign to tell his Bale to the Queen, and found his Courtly Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſes not ill repay'd. But that ſame Crafty Gallant, who underſtood per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly well what belonged to Amorous <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>amiliarities, found that Princeſs too deeply learned in Love, which diſguſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him, and cauſed him to return to his Amiable <hi>Nanon de Bois,</hi> a Taylors Daughter in the <hi>Fauxburgh St. Antoine. Well</hi>—ſaid the Grand Prior of <hi>France, the Favours of my pretty</hi> Nanon <hi>are worth all the Leavings of an</hi> Italian <hi>that has part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with her Honeſty.</hi> He therefore made the Dauphin and the Count of St. <hi>Maure</hi> privy to the Secret, who took a more than ordinary Delight to make ſport with it, by cauſing ſeveral Satyrical Lampoons to be thrown in at the Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows and into the Porches of the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop's Palace; among which this that follows was one.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:135703:12"/>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Reverend Patriarch,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>YOur Altar has been luſted after; a Lovely-feather'd Bird deſigned to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ve built her Neſt thee; but finding it nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>er proper nor clean, and too eaſie of Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>s, ſhe flew to another place. You ought <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>hinder your Swallow from Careſſing all the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſhe ſees, or at leaſt to faſten the Wires <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> her cloſer together.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>This Reproach put the Prelate into <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ind of Fet, not being able to Divine <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>m whence it came. But at length he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>forted up himſelf, as being accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>med to Coourtly Intreagues, which he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> very private, never making any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of 'em; ſuch were thoſe of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>chioneſs of <hi>Bretonvillers,</hi> the Abbeſs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Montmartre,</hi> the Pretty Sempſtreſs, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Beautiful Embroidereſs, whom <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> went to viſit ſo ſoon as it began to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Duskiſh.</p>
            <p>This formal piece of outward Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> was afraid leaſt it ſhould be pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ly reported, that he lighted his Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> before the Queens Altar; which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ld have rendered ſeveral She-Saints
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:135703:13"/>jealous of his carrying his Holy Water ſo far as St. <hi>Germains.</hi> All theſe Pious and Moral Conſiderations ſomewhat ſlackened our Doctor's Affection, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the coldneſs of his Miſtreſs, whoſe Politicks would not permit her to looſe him quite, tho ſhe cared not ſo much for continual Lip to Lip with an Old Sanctify'd Fornicator. In ſhort Monſieur the Archbiſhop forbore to viſit the Queen any more, unleſs it were to carry her his Benediction upon noted Holydays, or to ferret the Evil Spirits out of her chamber. On the other ſide our Princeſs who was a Paſſionate Lover of Amorous Combats, and who could not forbear the having ſtill ſome worthy Champions under her Standards, ſoon after declared War againſt another Loving Enemy. It happened then that this ſame tender Amazon had chafed her ſelf to that degree in the Field of <hi>Venus</hi> that ſhe fell ſick. For her Victory ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving enliven'd, her ſhe felt ſome effects of the heat of the Combat, which cauſed her to keep her Bed for ſome time: However ſhe was viſited all the while by the Reverend Father, Jeſuits and others in Religious Orders. But not one of thoſe Holy Fathers could comfort her
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:135703:13"/>with all their Learning. There was on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly one young Curate of St. <hi>Martin,</hi> whom that Princeſs had heard preach, who could inſtruct her, at leaſt as well as the Life of <hi>Clement</hi> VI. which ſhe fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently read, who commanded the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels to carry into Paradiſe thoſe that Dy'd coming in Pilgrimage to <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Young Prieſt was a Marry Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion, well ſhap'd, having a good Aſpect, very Fair, and much a Courtier. He needed no more to Charm beyond mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure a Woman of her Humour, who could not live without Square Caps, or Swords to guard her from the Fears that her Husbands ill ſucceſs inſpired into her. For which reaſon it was that the Lovely Patient in the time of her ſickneſs mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtered up together all the rare Qualities of her Amiable Curate. She alſo told her Confident the Marchioneſs of <hi>P—s,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat ſhe could not forget the Sermon ſhe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ad heard at St. <hi>Martins;</hi> that ever ſince, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er Heart had been warm'd with an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ent Devotion, and that ſhe ſhould be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>verjoy'd to ſee, in her ſickneſs, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>owerful Preacher.</p>
            <p>The Marchioneſs who underſtood <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er, lookt upon her with a fixt Eye, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd falling into a Laughter, told her ſhe
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:135703:14"/>would do her Endeavour that ſhe ſhould have the Benediction of the Pious Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate when ſhe pleaſed. <hi>Ah Marchioneſs,</hi> reply'd the Queen, <hi>thou ſpeakeſt this mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily and laughing, but I aſſure thee I am in love with his manner of Preaching. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> reply'd the Marchioneſs, <hi>I believe he is much better at handling a Text of Love. 'Tis true,</hi> ſaid the Queen, <hi>for he is a Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty Man, well turned, and whoſe Face ſpeaks him to be a Lover of Women; I would fain ſpeak with him. That's no hard matter to do, Madam,</hi> reply'd the Marchioneſs, <hi>for I know his Siſter who lives with Madam</hi> de Segnelay, <hi>and is as good a Girl as any is i' the World; I'll ſpeak to her this ver<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Day, and after ſuch a manner that ſhe ſhall have no ſuſpition of any thing. Do ſo, my Dear,</hi> reply'd the Queen, <hi>thou doſt no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> know what a kindneſs thou wilt do me to le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> me ſee the Curate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The next Day the Marchioneſs gave a Viſit to Madam <hi>de Seignelay,</hi> where ſhe ſaw <hi>Mademoiſelle de Fontaine,</hi> to whom ſhe ſpoke a thouſand things in Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of her Brother, and how highly the Queen was pleaſed with his laſt Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, and that ſhe would be gad to have ſome Diſcourſe now and then with a Perſon ſo Zealous and ſo Religious
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:135703:14"/>She added withal, That the Queen was a Woman of an Exemplary Devotion, that ſhe ſpent the greateſt part of her time in her Chappel, and that ſhe roſe every Night to ſay her Prayers, and to read the Lives of the Saints, particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of our Lady of <hi>Loretto,</hi> who is the greateſt Saint that ever was, and the moſt humble in all her Actions.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mademoiſelle de Fontaine</hi> was a little ſurpriſed at firſt to hear what a Portrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture the Marchioneſs made of the Queens Piety. To which the Damſel anſwered very civilly, that her Brother was very happy to have moved the heart of ſo great a Princeſs, and that ſhe would not fail to acquaint him with the good Tydings.</p>
            <p>After the Marchioneſs was gone, <hi>de la Fontaine</hi> gave Madam <hi>de Segnelay</hi> an Account of her Brother's Good For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, and ſhe related it again to her Husband, who Laught a long time at the Extraordinary Inclinations of the Queen, frequently ſaying in Merriment, <hi>That he who would pleaſe that Princeſs, muſt be of the Sanctify'd Order.</hi> I <hi>aſſure ye, Sir,</hi> ſaid the Marchioneſs of <hi>Segnelay</hi> Laughing, <hi>there are Perſons ſometimes to be me with of an Extraordinary Merit, who
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:135703:15"/>retire from the World to mind nothing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Great Buſineſs of their Salvation. Yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> may perhaps in time, Madam,</hi> reply'd th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Marqueſs with a ſmile of Deriſion, <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> brought to Love ſuch Men in imitation of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Pious a Queen, but have you a care of thoſe ſuttle Serpents that know ſo well to ſting La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies in their moſt ſenſible part.</hi>The Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſs farther told his Wife, that the Queen had always been a Lover of Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quettry, and Amorous Intrigues before ſhe went into <hi>England.</hi> You know moreover your ſelf that this Princeſs co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to the Court of <hi>France,</hi> appeared ſo Excellent an Artiſt in all her Gallan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, that the King himſelf had a ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Affection for her, and that his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty wrote in her Favour to King <hi>James</hi> as of a Perſon altogether Charming, and one that deſerved his Heart. And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> know my ſelf that in <hi>Italy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> ſhe was look<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> upon as one that held a private Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce with Count <hi>Don Quixote,</hi> and the Baron of <hi>Santifiori,</hi> who were both Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vals, yet agreed very well together.</p>
            <p>The marquiſs of <hi>Seignelay,</hi> who wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Secretary of State, would have told his Wife more, would the Orders which he received that Day from the King have permitted him to have ſtay'd longe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:135703:15"/>with her, ſo that he left her at his Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, where ſhe was not long alone how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever notwithſtanding his Abſence. For the <hi>Chevalier de Nouailles,</hi> Lieutenant General, whom ſhe Loved a Thouſand times better than her Husband, kept her Company like a Faithful Friend, and divertiſed her to the utmoſt of his power. But that which interrupted the Marchioneſſes Pleaſures deſerves to be here ſet down. That Lady had a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rot which one of the Pages, like an Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luckly Slipſtring, had taught to ſay, <hi>I'll tell Monſieur, Madam, if you let any Bod. open his Cabinet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This pratling <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ot diſturb'd the Loving Couple. For ſhe was afraid the Lacqueys had diſcovered ſomething of her Amours with the <hi>Chevalier de Nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ailes,</hi> and leaſt the noiſe of it ſhould wake her Husband's Jealouſies, who was Friend to Coquets, and had no ſuch Complacency for his Wife as to wear Horns becauſe they were of her making. Theſe Reaſons cauſed Madam <hi>Seignalay</hi> to return with all ſpeed to <hi>Paris,</hi> and deſire her Gallant to forbear his Viſits for ſome time, to take away all ſuſpici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of any ſuch thing as an Amorous In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trigue.
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:135703:16"/>But tis a very hard matter for us to appear what we are not, and they that would appear otherwiſe then they are, muſt take a great deal of pains. To this purpoſe the Marchioneſs went every Day to Maſs with the greateſt Devotion i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the World, and would hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be ſeen of any Body in hopes to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the moſt quick-ſighted. But Love who never looſes his Rights, and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered her to play this Game for a while, returned ſoon after more dangerous than ever, ſparkling in the Eyes of the Fair Lady with all his Graces, full of powerful Charms; which cauſed Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam <hi>de Seignelay</hi> to fall into a deep Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la choly and a profound vexation of mind that laſted a long time. Nay, ſhe fled the ſight of her Lover; believing that Abſence would Cure her: But a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las! Time has let us ſee, that Love is a Miſchief which Abſence cannot cure, and that it requires ſome more pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailing Medicament than that feeble Remedy.</p>
            <p>The Marchioneſs was ſometimes trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled that ſhe had liſtned to the Cheva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier. But being Young, ſhe did not think that Paſſion was ſo cleverly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veigh'd to the Heart through the Ears,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:135703:16"/>as through the Eyes, and therefore that the following Verſes which her Gallant would be always ſinging to her ſpoke truh.</p>
            <q>
               <l>At firſt a Toy we think it, tam'd with eaſe;</l>
               <l>But every thing in Love is to be fear'd,</l>
               <l>And ſhe that would be faithful, one to pleaſe,</l>
               <l>If once ſhe liſtens, ſhe's for ever ſnar'd.</l>
            </q>
            <p>The Marchioneſs of <hi>P—s,</hi> who had told the Queen how neatly ſhe had managed the Buſineſs between her and <hi>Mademoiſelle de la Fontaine</hi> in reference to her Brother, extreamly pleaſed that Princeſs, in hopes that the Complemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Prieſt would come to wait upon her without being put to the trouble of ſending for him. Theſe tickling Fancies rejoyced the Queens Heart, who was ſtill ſick, when Monſieur the Archbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, who could not as yet reſtrain his Affection for her, notwithſtanding the Reproaches he had undergone for her ſake, and the little Love which that Fair <hi>Venus</hi> reſerved for him, tho ſhe car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry'd it fairly with him by reaſon of her Misfortunes, flattering her ſelf that the Head of the Council of <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV's Conſcience, together with his Majeſty, might
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:135703:17"/>be ſerviceable to her in her Deſigns and Neceſſities, came to give her a Viſit.</p>
            <p>The Prelate therefore being alighted out of his Coach, was by Mrs. <hi>Labad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> conducted into the Queens Chamber, who received him very civily, and gave him an Account of her Sickneſs, to which the <hi>Sorbonne</hi> Doctor anſwered with much tenderneſs, tho he ſtay'd not long with his Fair Minioneſs, which nothing at all ſurprized her; for ſhe was already accuſtomed to ſee a Lover who was grown very chary of his Viſits; a thing that nothing diſpleaſed her, ſeeing her chiefeſt aim was only to preſerve his friendſhip. On the other ſide, the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate of St. <hi>Mart<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n,</hi> who had underſtood from his Siſter and ſeveral others the great Commendations which the Queen gave him, had conceived ſuch a high Opinion of himſelf, that for the fixing of his Happineſs, he reſolved to go and pay his Devoirs to her Majeſty, and to let her underſtand how much he was overjoy'd to hear himſelf applauded by a Perſon of her Illuſtrious Character and tranſcending worth, which over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loaded that Princeſs with a ſatisfaction not to be expeſſed; and at the ſame time a Page came to inform her, That
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:135703:17"/>the Curate of St. <hi>Martin</hi>'s was in the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle Court, and that hedeſired, with her Majeſties permiſſion, to pay his reſpects to her.</p>
            <p>At thoſe words the Queen ſeem'd to be in a ſtrange diſcompoſure of Mind, ſo that ſhe had hardly ſtrength enough to conceal her joy, which was extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary, as generally it happens at the beginning of freſh Amours. But her Amorous Tranſports being a little calmed, ſhe ordered the Curate to be ſent for up, who after ſeveral Pedantic Scrapes, Cringes of a Journyman-Tay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor, and affected motions of his Head, told her with all the Rhetoric, and the beſt ſtudy'd language that he had, how happy he was in having the Honour to pleaſe a Princeſs of ſo great a Judgment, and whoſe Vertue made ſuch a noiſe i' the World. The Queen ordered an Elbow-Chair to be brought him, which the Curate had ſo much Manners or Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcretion to refuſe, but the Dutcheſs of <hi>Portſmouth,</hi> who was in the Chamber, told him very Complementally, that he ought to obey the Queens Orders. That day there was nothing diſcourſed of but Devotion and Piety, and Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur the Curate ſpoke like an Angel.
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:135703:18"/>Among other things he talk'd Seraphi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of the Holy Exultations that were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired into him by reading the Bleſſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Works of <hi>Catherine</hi> of <hi>Siena,</hi> who fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> her infinite Merit, and her Devout Life had rendered her ſelf worthy to be th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Spouſe of Chriſt, who deſcended from Heaven on purpoſe to Marry her.</p>
            <p>The Marchioneſs of <hi>P—s,</hi> by th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> aid of her Bigottry, prolonged th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Converſation with ſeveral other Tale<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of the ſame Nature: Inſomuch that they alſo chatted of the Arrival of St. <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> who was to make his Entry int<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Paris</hi> with all the pomp in practiſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Saints. At what time th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Dutcheſs of <hi>Portſmouth</hi> pull d out of he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Pocket a Letter which ſhe had receive<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> out of <hi>Bretagne</hi> from the Nunnery o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Joy, written to her by Madam <hi>de Plein</hi> her Aunt, who was Abbeſs of that San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctify'd place, wherein ſhe ſet forth th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Penances ſhe enjoyn'd her Nuns, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> how happy they were that mortify'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> their Fleſh in this World.</p>
            <p>Such Godly Diſcourſe began to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend the <hi>Queen,</hi> who broke off the Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Converſation, by talking of New and the Gallantries of the Court. Al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> which time the Curate ſhew'd great Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervedneſs
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:135703:18"/>and Moderation by judging <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>udiciouſly and ſoberly of the Perſons mentioned; which begot him ſo much <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he more eſteem among the Ladies. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which the Dutcheſs of <hi>Portſmouth,</hi> and <hi>Madam P—s</hi> having other Buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs left the <hi>Queen</hi> and the Curate alone together.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Queen</hi> thus finding her ſelf at li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, ordered Monſieur the Curate to draw his Chair a little nearer, which he durſt not do till after the <hi>Queen</hi> had commanded him ſeveral times. <hi>Well, Sir,</hi> ſaid ſhe, <hi>you may now believe your ſelf the Moſt Fortunate of Men.</hi> The Curate bluſh'd to ſee the <hi>Queen</hi> ſo eager upon the buſineſs, but anſwered her only with a Sigh, which gave the Illuſtrious Ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour'd to underſtand that her new Lover was not altogether inſenſible of her for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardneſs. And the Curate alſo began to feel his imagination ſomewhat Warm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, when the Princeſſes of <hi>Soiſſons</hi> and <hi>Conti</hi> came to viſit the <hi>Queen,</hi> who had hid her Curate between the Wall and the Bedſide, where being tyr'd with the tedious Chat of the Viſitants he laid him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf gently down and took a Nap.</p>
            <p>When the Princeſſes were gone, the <hi>Queen</hi> who thought the time of their
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:135703:19"/>ſtay to be an Age, tript back to her Chamber, and drawing the Curtains of her Bed, beheld her Lovely <hi>Adonis</hi> faſt a ſleep, which grieved her to the heart. For that Princeſs was no Admirer of Drouſie Galants; as ſhe would often tell the Dutcheſs of <hi>Portſmouth,</hi> fetching a deep ſigh with all, That indeed the King her Husband went to Bed betimes; <hi>But why was it, my Dear,</hi> continu'd ſhe, —<hi>becauſe he Loved Sleeping the beſt of any Man in the World.</hi> The <hi>Queen</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſitting down cloſe by her Lover, made a little noiſe, which wakened him, tho more doz'd with ſhame than with ſleep. <hi>Ah! My Dear,</hi> ſaid ſhe, <hi>preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, What a Coward you are!</hi> — Such words as thoſe would have raiſed the Courage of any Curate that ſaw the Shepherd's Hour at hand, and had had any Mettle in him. But the Great Loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by fetch'd only a deep <hi>Alas!</hi> Accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny'd with ſeveral Complaints, which could not pay that Princeſs the ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction ſhe wanted. I know not whether it were the Preſence of a Perſon of her Character, or her too eaſie Condeſcenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which had rendered our Abbot, as it were immoveable and void of ſence; but certain it is, he did not behave him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:135703:19"/>like one who was to receive ſuch new Favours from a <hi>Queen,</hi> being ſtrangely nonpluſs'd and quite out of or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, tho he were naturally a Boon Blade that never let an Opportunity ſlip, beſides that he was a great Lover of Nocturnal Rendevouzes.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Queen,</hi> who was offended at the ſtupidneſs of her Lover, left him, and retired into her Cabinet to ruminate upon what ſhe had done. During this Interval, our Monarch was earneſtly ſeeking for her, to ſhew her certain Letters which he had received out of <hi>Ireland</hi> from <hi>Tyrconnel</hi> and <hi>Lauſun,</hi> giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him an Account of a ſuppoſed Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, by the Death of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>arſhal <hi>Schomberg,</hi> and the Wound which King <hi>William</hi> had received by the bruſh of a Cannon-Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let.</p>
            <p>Theſe Tydings overjoy'd the Court to that degree, that they made Bonfires, and revell'd in Extravagancies even to Madneſs for above eight Days together. All the Ladies and Lords ſpent their time in Debauches, Balls, Comedies, Opera's and whatever elſe might ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie their Senſes.</p>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:135703:20"/>
            <p>The Dauphin entertained the Iluſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Aſſembly at <hi>Choiſi,</hi> with an Extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Magnificence, and gave 'em all the Divertiſements imaginable. The Ladies went with the Princes and Lords a Hawking with their Feathers in their Hats, and Accoutred in Scarlet Juſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cores. The Princeſſes of <hi>Conti, du Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ere</hi> and <hi>Soiſſons,</hi> wee Indefatigable Racers, which engaged the Dauphin, the Duke of <hi>Chartres</hi> and others in the ſame ſport, tho they were glad to yield the Victory to thoſe Amiable Heroeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes.</p>
            <p>The next Day the Queen, who had not yet well recovered her ſtrength, ſtrook in with that ſame Troop of Gods and Goddeſſes, on purpoſe to take a little Air, and ſhare in the pleaſure of that Princely Entertainment, attended by the Dutcheſs of <hi>Portſmouth,</hi> the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chioneſs of <hi>Seignelay,</hi> Madam <hi>P—s</hi> and ſeveral other Lords and Ladies. His Majeſty alſo, and the Prince's who ſaw that the Preſence of the <hi>Queen</hi> had ang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented the Number of the Aſſembly, ordered the following Night to be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightened with Fireworks, as a Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny how glad he was to ſee her. Our Monarch alſo, who knew that the <hi>Quee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:135703:20"/>was a paſſionate Lover of Muſick, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered a moſt Charming Conſort, and Symphony to be provided againſt the next Day, for her more ſplendid En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment. And the next Day they returned to <hi>Paris,</hi> where they went to an Opera of <hi>Apollo</hi> and the Muſes, which was repreſented in the Palace, and the next Day to another of <hi>Cephalus</hi> and <hi>Procris.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By this time the Curate of St. <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin,</hi> who had reflected upon the <hi>Queens</hi> Favours, and his own want of Courage, was ready to Hang himſelf for having loſt ſo fair an opportunity. <hi>Coward as thou wert,</hi> ſaid the vext Lover to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, that could not anſwer the forward Advances of ſo Adorable a Princeſs, nor recover thy ſelf into a Condition to improve thy Good Fortune! But I believe the Great Merit of that Incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable Lady bewitched me, ſince all that make a Man to be a Man was Inſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible and motionleſs within me.</p>
            <p>Theſe Reflexions being over, our Galant reſolved to ſhew his Miſtreſs all his Valour, and to acquit himſelf after another manner for the future, or elſe to be revenged upon his Carkaſs. As for the <hi>Queen,</hi> in the midſt of all the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:135703:21"/>Pleaſures wherewith the Court had en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained her, ſhe had not forgot to ponder upon the laſt Advanture that had befallen her. But in regard ſhe had not ſpoken a word of it, to any Body, ſhe the more comforted up her ſelf with making a Myſtery of her Amorous Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets. On the other ſide, the Curate who burned with a deſire to ſhew the value of his Parts, adventured to wait upon his Princeſs, whom he found mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing in a Gallery that led to the Pr. of <hi>Wales</hi>'s Chamber. So ſoon as the <hi>Queen</hi> beheld her Gallant, ſhe fell a Bluſhing. But having recovered her ſelf from that diſſorder, which was the effect of her deſire, ſhe requeſted him to walk into her Chamber, where they preſently fell to work about thoſe Pleaſures which the ſweeteſt of Paſſions infuſes. Our Amiable <hi>Queen</hi> of <hi>Cyprus,</hi> who appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed altogether Charming in thoſe Delici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Minutes, ſoon forgot her Sorrow for having diſcovered her Weakneſs to her Victor. So true it is that all our Deſigns againſt Love are but of a ſhort continuance. When a Heart becomes ſenſible once of the Charms of that Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, it always follows the Propenſity that beck us it along. The <hi>Queen</hi> has
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:135703:21"/>promis'd her ſelf a thouſand times that ſhe would never be in Love any more, the Pains and Vexations of which Paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſurpaſs all the Joys which that ſame Bandy-legg'd Deity infuſes into us. But to what purpoſe all our vain Reflexions. Here is our Illuſtrious Penitent more tender than ever, half Swooning away in the Arms of her Lover, and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging no other Felicity but that of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moreous ſatisfaction.</p>
            <p>But Monſieur the Curate, who held his Divine <hi>Queen</hi> faſt lockt in his Arms, and Kiſs d her tenderly all the while, was at his Wits end when Mrs. <hi>Labady</hi> calling through the Key-hole of the Door, which was faſtened within ſide, told her <hi>Majeſty,</hi> That the Dutcheſs of <hi>Chartres</hi> and <hi>Maine</hi> were alighted from their Coach at St. <hi>Germains,</hi> with an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to Viſit her immediately. The two Lovrs, who had not a little towſed and rumpled one another with their A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morous Careſſes, put themſelves to rights as well as they could: And that being done, the Curate whip'd away down a Back pair of Stairs, and went home, while-the <hi>Queen</hi> went to take a Walk with the Dutcheſſes in the Galleries of the <hi>Lonvre,</hi> which are full of Paintings,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:135703:23"/>deſcribing the Battles of <hi>Alexander</hi> and <hi>Darius,</hi> done by <hi>M. le Brun.</hi> The <hi>Queen</hi> ſaid, He was an Excellent Artiſt for that ſort of Painting, but that he was not ſo good for Drawing a Face. <hi>'Tis true, Madam,</hi> reply'd the Dutcheſs of <hi>Main, that</hi> M. Migniart <hi>paints more natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally and to the Life then</hi> M. le Brun, <hi>who is only for Hiſtory.</hi> Thus our Princeſſes were diſputing the Buſineſs together, when the Dauphin, St. <hi>Maure,</hi> and the Princeſſes of <hi>Conti</hi> and <hi>Liſtebonne</hi> Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived.</p>
            <p>So ſoon as the Princeſs of <hi>Conti</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held the <hi>Queen</hi> at a diſtance, ſhe fell a Laughing, and Whiſpering the <hi>Dauphin</hi> in the Ear, <hi>Yonder,</hi> ſaid ſhe, <hi>is the Duke of</hi> Vendoſme<hi>'s Amiable Miſtreſs — Oh my dear Siſttr,</hi> reply'd the Monſieur, <hi>looking upon her with a Waggiſh Eye, our Prior has too dainty a Palate, to be ſatisfy'd with ſo common a Diſh.</hi> The Princeſs, who was that Day in a Good Humour and reſolved to be merry, was going to ſpeak more of her mind, when the <hi>Queen</hi> and the Dutcheſſes came to ſalut<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> her, and they talk'd of nothing bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Paintings and Portraitures. At the ſame time the Count of St. <hi>Maure</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed their going altogether to <hi>M. Mig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niart</hi>'s,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:135703:23"/>where they ſhould ſee Accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh'd Beauties, and among the reſt the Portraiture of a Daughter of one of the Advocates of the Council, which was the Lovelieſt Face that ever he beheld. The <hi>Dauphin</hi> approv'd the Deſign; ſo that all the Ladies took Coach immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>M. Mignart</hi> told the Company he would ſhew 'em his firſt Room, which was full of the Pictures of all the Lords in the Kingdom. <hi>There is one,</hi> ſaid the <hi>Queen, I know very well;</hi> which happen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be <hi>Lauſun</hi>'s, and which was done ſo well to the Life, that it wanted only to ſpeak.</p>
            <p>After they had a long time viewed all thoſe Pieces, the Count of St. <hi>Maure</hi> deſired the Painter to ſhew 'em the Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traitures of the Ladies, which <hi>M. Mig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niart</hi> did accordingly. At what time the Count drawing near the <hi>Dauphin,</hi> ſhew'd him the Picture of the Fair <hi>Gou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jon,</hi> ſaying to him with a paſſionate Air, <hi>Sir, the Original of this Copy deſerves the Affection of ſome Gallant Perſon.</hi> Monſieur found the Portraiture a thouſand times Hand ſomer than the Count had deſcrib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it, but return'd him no other An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer than only this, <hi>Do you believe,</hi> ſaid
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:135703:22"/>he, <hi>that there are any perſons ſo Beautiful in the World, and that this Damſel is ſo Charming as the Painter has Drawn her?</hi> Monſieur <hi>Migniart</hi> who over-heard him, made Anſwer to the <hi>Dauphin,</hi> that he had not flatter'd her in his Painting, but that the Picture was like her, not ſhe like the Picture. Which laſt words made the <hi>Dauphin</hi> more carefully exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine the Lovely Lineaments of that peerleſs Minioneſs, which put him into a deep Study. But the <hi>Queen</hi> and the Princeſſes, who had much ado to brook the Commendations that were beſtow'd upon that Beautiful Portraiture, out of meer Jealouſie and Deſpite, told the <hi>Dauphin,</hi> That ſhe had a Froward Wild Look, which made the Lords fall a Laughing, who plainly ſaw the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. More eſpecially the Princeſs of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti, Sir,</hi> ſaid ſhe to the <hi>Dauphin</hi> ſmiling, <hi>in time you will fall in Love with Women, for you look veny wiſtly upon 'em. Provided they wexe like your ſelf, Madam,</hi> reply d the Monſieur, <hi>I could willingly conſent to be in Love.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After this Illuſtrious Company had left the Painter, every one retir'd to their own Habitations, except the <hi>Dau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phin,</hi> who followed the Princeſs of
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:135703:22"/>
               <hi>Conti,</hi> his Confident, Home, where he ſpent the remainder of the Day in tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling a Hundred Stories of the Court: And the Duke of <hi>Vendome</hi> and the Count of St. <hi>Maure,</hi> who alſo met him there, had their ſhare of the merriment.</p>
            <p>The next Day our Monarch, who had not ſeen the Queen for ſome time, hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing been taken up with the Great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion which Madam <hi>de Maintenon</hi> infu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes into him by vertue of the Holy Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter with which ſhe beſprinkles the Bol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of his Bed every Morning, and a great Roſary which ſhe makes him al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways wear about his Arm, this Prince, I ſay, with his <hi>Pater Noſter</hi>'s, went to Viſit his Miſtreſs, who receiv'd him very Civily, as ſhe was wont to do. After ſome ſerious Diſcourſe, the King drew near his Princeſs to Careſs her; and the firſt thing his majeſty did, was to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace her tenderly, and kiſs her ſeveral times; but the Queen who ſpy'd his Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary about his Wriſt, ask'd him, Why he carry'd his <hi>Pater Noſter</hi>'s ſo familiar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. <hi>Oh—Madam,</hi> cryd the King, <hi>there is an extraordinary Vertue in this Wood. Yes, Sir,</hi> reply'd the <hi>Queen, there is no queſtion of it—But do you know the Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of this Roſary in the moſt Amorous Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nutes?
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:135703:24"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:135703:24"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:135703:25"/>It cools the moſt inflam'd Paſſion, and terrifies the Heart with thoſe ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ings of Conſcience that many times proves deadly. 'Tis very true,</hi> reply'd the King, <hi>pulling off his Roſary, I have found my ſelf good for nothing ever ſince I wore it. But 'tis the Advice of my Confeſſor and Madam</hi> de Maintenon, <hi>who have aſſured me, that by ſaying my</hi> Ave Maries <hi>ſeveral times a Day to the Holy Virgin with this Roſary, no mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune ſhall befal either my Perſon or my Kingdom. You know, Madam,</hi> continu'd the King, <hi>that</hi> Lewis XIII. <hi>Rſigned his Crown to the protection of that Holy Patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. Oh, Sir,</hi> ſaid the <hi>Queen</hi> with a mournful utterance, <hi>talk no more of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigning Crowns, the very remembrance of it kills me. I would pray to St.</hi> Stephen <hi>and St.</hi> Lewis <hi>too a thouſand times oftner than I do, if they would but reſtore me to that which I have loſt. In the mean time, I find that the Saints are as great Cheats as Men and that there is no relying upon any thing in this World. Why, Madam,</hi> reply <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the King in a kind of Aſtoniſhment, <hi>did your Saint ever make you any promiſe? A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> others do,</hi> ſaid the <hi>Queen, who aſſure us o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> their ſuccour in our Diſtreſſes. However<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Madam,</hi> reply'd the King, <hi>the Saint<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> have a great power, and we rarely looſe th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:135703:25"/>Effects of that Devotion which we pay 'em. Some indeed there are, Sir,</hi> ſaid ſhe, <hi>that when 'tis for their Intereſt, hearken to us in purſuance of their deſigns.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our Monarch, who perceiv'd that a Devout Converſation did but render his Fair Maiſtreſs inſenſible of the Pleaſures of Love, chang'd his Diſcourſe, and told her with a paſſionate Air, That one Kiſs tenderly imprinted by her fair Lips, would reſtore Life to the Dead. The <hi>Queen</hi> who united Love and Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion together, made Anſwer to the King after a Languiſhing manner, That were it not for the ſweet Minutes that a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon Enamour'd taſts, it would not be worth the while to live one Day. <hi>'Tis true Charming Princeſs,</hi> ſaid the King, <hi>that is the moſt ſenſible part. Alas! Sir,</hi> reply'd the <hi>Queen</hi> half in a Swoon, <hi>harp no more upon that ſtring, for I feel my ſelf teady to faint.</hi> The King who perceived the <hi>Queen</hi> in a Swooning Fit that caus'd her to throw her ſelf upon the Bed, was preparing to aſſiſt her; but the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany coming in prevented his Sedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ity.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Queen</hi> being come to her ſelf ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted the Viſit of Monſieur the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop, who found her a little heated,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:135703:26"/>tho ſhe had made uſe of her Fan to cool her ſelf; for the Vapours of her imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation heightened by the preſence of our Great Prince, were not ſo eaſily laid. The Venerable Apoſtle there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, when the King was gone, began an Amorous Conſolation, vowing and proteſting to her whatever Love could inſpire into him. On the other ſide the <hi>Queen</hi> a thouſand times aſſur'd him with her uſual Addreſs, that ſhe lovd him better than her ſelf; which ſatisfy'd the Prelate, who pretended that all the Affection of a Woman was due to him, ſince Nature had bequeathed him the choiceſt of her Gifts.</p>
            <p>Their Diſcourſe was intermix'd, for that between whiles they talkd of the Affairs of <hi>England,</hi> and of King <hi>James</hi>'s Return, who was then going into <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> but was to return into <hi>France</hi> in a ſhort time by the Advice of <hi>Tyrconne</hi> and <hi>Lauſun. Here,</hi> ſaid the <hi>Queen, is a Letter from the Lord</hi> Killmallock, <hi>which gives me an account of the Death of the Sieur</hi> de St. Ruth, <hi>a</hi> French <hi>Officer and very Valiant, who was ſlain in the heat of the Fight. In truth, Madam,</hi> ſaid our Protector of the <hi>Surbonne, the loſs of ſuch a Worthy Officer as the Sieur</hi> de St. Ruth,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:135703:26"/>
               <hi>is a very great loſs to</hi> France. <hi>'Tis very <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rue,</hi> reply'd the <hi>Queen, but theſe are the fruits of War. I long to ſee the Count of</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a ſun; <hi>for I have a World of things to ſay <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o him. Madam,</hi> reply'd Monſieur the Archbiſhop, <hi>I have heard you ſpeak of the E. of</hi> Tyrconnel; <hi>and I have heard he is an</hi> Iriſh <hi>Man. Yes, my Dear,</hi> reply'd the <hi>Queen, and of mean Extraction to boot. He same into</hi> England <hi>young, where he was a Lacquey for ten years together, and afterwards met with a</hi> Catholick <hi>Maſter, who prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red him to the Duke of</hi> York, <hi>in the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of one of his Gentlemen. During which time he did his Lord ſo many good Services, that he loved him ſo well as to favour him with his good Will, and to entruſt him with ſome part of his Secrets; ſo that at laſt King</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ames <hi>thought good to make him Deputy of</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>reland, <hi>in recompence of his Fidelity. Such <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>as the Eash of</hi> Tyronnel<hi>'s Fortune, which was not a little to be admired. 'tis true,</hi> ſaid the Archbiſhop, <hi>that people of mean Extraction riſe to the higheſt degrees of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour; all things are governed by Luck and Chance—But</hi> I <hi>think</hi> I <hi>have heard ſay, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat formerly his Wife had been a very hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome Woman. I'll aſſure you, Sir,</hi> reply'd <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he <hi>Queen,</hi> I <hi>always took her to be one of the moſt amiable perſons i' the World. Firſt ſhe
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:135703:27"/>had a great deal of Wit, ſhe was well-ſhap'd, her Converſation ſweet und merry, her Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion incomparable, with large grey Eyes and very paſſionate; and then ſhe deſerved the Affection of an Honeſt Gentleman for the ſake of her Devotion, which was extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary in a Woman bred as ſhe was in the pleaſures of the World. The King of</hi> France <hi>was not inſenſible of her Charms,</hi> continu'd the <hi>Queen</hi> ſmiling; I <hi>know in good part, that the King fell in Love with her, and the King, my Husband, would have been dab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, finding her worthy of his Affection; which made me Marry her to</hi> Tyrconnel <hi>ſooner than</hi> I <hi>would have done, on purpoſe to break off that Familiarity which did not a little trouble me. But ſince that, we have been very good Friends, and if Heaven had proſpered our deſigns, we had been inſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable. But no more of this mournful Recital, it would carry me too far. With all my heart,</hi> anſwered our Metropolitan Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiff, embracing her tenderly, telling her withal, that King <hi>James</hi> had no true reaſon to Love any Woman i'the World to the prejudice of ſuch an Amiable Princeſs as her ſelf. <hi>Ah! My Dear,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed the <hi>Queen</hi> ſmiling, <hi>Men natureally love change, tho they can give no reaſon for it. If the Dutcheſs of</hi> G—n <hi>would
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:135703:27"/>have liſtned to my dear Husband, ſhe had been one of his Miſtreſſes; but ſhe had more Vertue.</hi> The <hi>Queen</hi> would have purſu'd the Hiſtory of King <hi>James</hi>'s Amours, but that ſhe was prevented by the Dutcheſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of <hi>Orleance</hi> and <hi>Bourbon,</hi> who came to ask her, Whither ſhe would go to the Chappel Royal of <hi>vincennes,</hi> to hear the Abbot <hi>Boileau,</hi> who was then a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Preacher. She conſented, and the Archbiſhop carried the Ladies in his Coach to the Chappel, and then went Home to give Orders to his Official <hi>M. Cheron</hi> againſt the next day, touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Surbonne.</hi> But our Princeſs, who was prepoſſeſſed with the Merits of the Curate of St. <hi>Martin,</hi> did not think the Abbot <hi>Boileau</hi> ſo Eloquent as he was reputed to be, tho the Dutcheſſes of <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leance</hi> and <hi>Bourbon</hi> told her ſeveral times that they never had heard ſo brave, nor ſo learned a Man. <hi>For my part,</hi> reply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the <hi>Queen, I look upon him to be too po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pular, and that he has not Fire enough in his Expreſſions.</hi> I <hi>know not that, Madam,</hi> anſwered the Dutcheſs of <hi>Orleans, but he is admired by all the World. Oh Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> ſaid the <hi>Queen, had this famous Preacher no more than your Approbation, it were enough to render him happy.</hi> The
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:135703:28"/>
               <hi>Queen</hi> pronounced thoſe words with ſomething of an Air of Deriſion which no ways pleaſed the Dutcheſs, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſome Days after told the King that th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Queen</hi> was ſo proud that it was no won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſhe was Dethroned. But the King who had a Kindneſs for the <hi>Queen,</hi> mad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it his Buſineſs to reconcile the Dutcheſs and her together; ſo that ever ſince they have been very good Friends.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Dauphin,</hi> who ſtill viſited the Princeſs of <hi>Turenne</hi> privately, by the cunning management of her Squire M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>du Mont,</hi> who found a way to intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce the Monſieur at a back pair o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Stairs, without any notice taken of him and who has ſince managed all his Amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Intrigues with that dexterity, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Court has been kept in ſgnorance This Squire adviſed the <hi>Dauphin</hi> neve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to viſit the Princeſs till about Ten a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Clock at Night, when her Husband would be at play at the Dutcheſs of <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours,</hi> which Monſieur, who loves ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creſiy in Love, carefully obſerved to do; remembring the Cuſtom of one o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Dukes and Peers of <hi>France</hi> lately Dead, who hired a Houſe in the ſtree<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Grenelle,</hi> the backſide of which joyned cloſe to a Palace where lived a very
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:135703:28"/>pretty Woman, for whoſe ſake, that he might privately enjoy her, he broke a door out of one Houſe into the other; by which means they met as often as they pleaſed, and no Body the wiſer.</p>
            <p>Madam <hi>de Turenne,</hi> who paſſionately Loved the <hi>Dauphin,</hi> ſtaid for him one Evening in her Chamber with great im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patience. At length when the <hi>Dauphin</hi> came, he found her ſomewhat melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly; of which when the Monſieur asked her the reaſon ſomewhat ſurlily, ſhe made anſwer, That 'twas her Mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune to have an Amorous Delicacy quite oppoſite to the Humour and Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius of her Lover. The <hi>Dauphin,</hi> whom the ſport of Hunting renders a little Ruſtic, and who reſerves no great po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liteneſs for Ladies, anſwered her ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what rudely, as he roſe up from her, That Women by their little Tricks, made Love Capricious. Upon which the Princeſs, underſtanding the humour of her Gallant, ran to embrace him, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to him at the ſame time, <hi>Ah, my dear Prince, you have not wherewithal to ſatisfie a Tender Lover,</hi> which words pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced with an extraordinary paſſion, made the <hi>Dauphin</hi> fall a Laughing, who told her that ſhe knew that beſt. Upon
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:135703:29"/>that, the Princeſs of <hi>Turenne</hi> perceiving ſhe ſhould never be able to alter the <hi>Dauphin</hi>'s Clowniſh Diſpoſition, fell a Laughing as well as he: And ſo that E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vening was ſpent in Toying after the Monſieurs manner, and Monſieur having uttered ſome agreeable Expreſſion to the <hi>Princeſs,</hi> contrary to his Cuſtom, ſhe returned him her Thanks after a very Courtly manner. But at length the night being far ſpert the two Lovers parted well ſatisfied the one with the other.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Prince</hi> of <hi>Turenne,</hi> who had been playing till it was late at Madam <hi>de Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours,</hi> being by that time returned, was deſirous to go to Bed; but finding it extreamly tumbled, asked his Wife the reaſon of it, who was at her Wits end for not having cauſed it to be made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain before her Husband came Home. So that the diſorder ſhe was in, confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the <hi>Princes</hi> Suſpicions ſo much the more; but being come to her ſelf again, ſhe told him, <hi>She had been very much troubled with the Headach, and that ſhe had lain down ſeveral times to alleviate her pain. 'Tis very well, Madam,</hi> reply'd the <hi>Prinee,</hi> with a diſcontented Look, <hi>and now you are Cur'd, I am ſick.</hi> The
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:135703:29"/>Diſconſolate Lady, not knowing what elſe in the World to do, endeavoured by all the moſt tender Careſſes imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable to recover the <hi>Prinee</hi> into a good Humour, who for his part little mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his Wifes Gallantries, as being enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged at leaſt in Intrigues ſo far diſtinct; and not having any kindneſs for <hi>Made<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moiſelle de Ventadour,</hi> whom he had Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried for the Intereſt of his Family only, as being the greateſt Heireſs in the Kingdom. For theſe Reaſons he treated his Wife but very roughly, as not hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any Tenderneſs for her, being whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly taken up with the Counteſs <hi>de Rourre,</hi> who had loſt her Husband in the Battel of <hi>Flerus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That Lovely Woman had the knack always to obtain an infinite number of Admirers. And all the Sparks of <hi>Venus</hi> that beheld her, burn'd with a deſire to be fettered in her Chains. We have ſaid of the Princeſs of <hi>Turenne</hi> that ſhe Lov'd with a certain Delicacy and Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioſity, which conſiſted in a thouſand little Punctilios. On the other ſide, the Counteſs <hi>de Rourre</hi> little car'd whether a Man Lov'd her or no, ſo ſhe could di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertiſe her ſelf, and provided her Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers ſent her Magnificent Preſents, ſhe
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:135703:30"/>left them the Liberty to change as often as they pleaſed, reſerving alſo the ſame liberty to her ſelf. And therefore it may be ſaid, That this Lady was a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed Coquet: But notwithſtanding this ſame Coquettry, the <hi>Dauphin</hi> allow'd her a ſhare of his Favours as well as the <hi>Princeſs</hi> of <hi>Turenne,</hi> and many others. But this not being to my purpoſe, I ſhall ſay no more of it but only thus much, That her Carriage being none of the Modeſteſt, nor ſo Diſcreet as it ſhould be, vexed the very Soul of the Count her Husband, who would frequently Curſe the fatal Day that had j<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yn'd him to that ſickle Wag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tail.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Dauphin,</hi> who after the Death of her Husband, had given the Counteſs <hi>du Rourre</hi> a very fair Houſe near St. <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nore</hi>'s Gate, went frequently to viſit her, and diligently waited on her, as one of the moſt Amiable of his Miſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. On the other ſide, that Charming Lady made uſe of all her Artifices, her Amorous Dalliances and Tender Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſſes, to preſerve a Heart which had no great Inclination to Love, as being more affected with ſporting in the Woods than between the Sheets.</p>
            <pb n="57" facs="tcp:135703:30"/>
            <p>'Tis the Nature of Coquetts to force their Humour to a Complyance with that of their Lovers: For by that means they always keep a good Correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence with them. So that the <hi>Dauphin</hi> who had not thoſe winning ſatisfactions that ſeaſon the Ragoo's of Love, could not forbear the having an infinite Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs for that Lady. One Day that ſhe was in her Cabinet, and that ſhe was ſenſible of a more then uſual tenderneſs, her Illuſtrious Lover came in, to whom ſhe ſaid not a word. At what time Monſieur admiring at the ſilence of his Incomparable Minioneſs, demanded the reaſon, and at the ſame time gave her a tender Kiſs. <hi>Ah! My dear Prince,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd ſhe with a ſign, <hi>I was muſtering up all my Good Luck, and that great Idea de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived me of my Speech. Madam,</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer'd the Monſieur, <hi>that defect is heredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary to your Ladyſhip, becauſe you are half a</hi> Norman. <hi>My dear Prince,</hi> ſaid the Counteſs, <hi>you take me one way, and I mean another: For my meaning was, that I was ſo Charm'd with being never ſo little belov'd by ſo great a Prince, that at that very mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment I had loſt the ordinary uſe of my Tongue. I underſtand ye, Madam,</hi> reply'd the Prince with a ſmile, <hi>but by thoſe words,</hi>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:135703:31"/>never ſo little, <hi>you ſeem to miſtruſt that I am not wholly at your Service. This is an injuſtice done to my ſincere Love, and the real Affection I have for ye.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Upon that the Counteſs roſe from her Seat, and went to embrace her dear Lover who is extreamly pleas'd when a Woman that has a Kindneſs for him prevents him with ſome little Addreſſes I know not what they did more; but believe that in all probability Lover was not ſatisfy'd with only bare Expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
            <p>However it were, our <hi>Queen</hi> in Tribulation, who could not long endure the Abſence of Monſieur the Curate, ſent for him by one of her Gentlemen, under pretence that her little <hi>Prince of Wales</hi> was ſick, and that ſhe was extreamly afflicted for fear of loſing a dear Child, upon whoſe Life all her Hopes depend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Now the Curate either out of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, or for ſome other Reaſons, durſt not ſo frequently viſit his <hi>Princeſs,</hi> ſo that the <hi>Prieſt</hi> was over joy'd to find him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf ſent for. To which purpoſe he cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to his Remembrance all the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures he had taſted in the Enjoyment of ſo Adorable a perſon, and the good Fortune which he hop'd to reap from
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:135703:31"/>his good Service. All theſe great Ideas made the Lover to go up into his Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, where he rubb'd himſelf from Head to Foot with Eſſence of <hi>Jaſſemine,</hi> ſcour'd his Hands with Paſt of Almonds to make 'em feel ſmooth, and powder'd his Hair more than he was wont to do; and after he had thus trickt and ſpru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced himſelf up, he went to viſit the Queen about Six a Clock in the Evening. For at that Hour ſhe ſent him word ſhe ſhould be alone, becauſe her Court would be at the Opera, or at other Divertiſements of the Carneval Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</p>
            <p>Monſieur the Curate found his Charming Miſtreſs and the little <hi>Prince</hi>'s Nurſe bemoaning the Illuſtrious Infant, and ſcar'd at the thoughts of his Death <hi>Oh,</hi> ſaid the Afflicted <hi>Princeſs, muſt I looſe the only Bleſſing that is left me in this World! St.</hi> Winifred, <hi>accept my Offerings and hear my Vows, and ſanctifie the Prayers which I make to thee, Divine Queen of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>During this Ejaculation, the <hi>Queen</hi> caſt an Eye upon her Gallant, then upon his Knees, that he might partici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pate in the Devotion of the <hi>Frinceſs,</hi> who at the ſame time took him by the
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:135703:32"/>Hand and led him into her Chamber. There ſhe ask'd him his Advice about the ſick Prince, and what he thought of his Diſtemper. To which the Curate anſwered after he had put her in hpes, that if he ſhould happen to Die, it was a Loſs that might be repair'd, ſince her Majeſties Youth could not want Heirs to her Husbands Throne. Thoſe words re-cheard the Queens Heart, who ſeem'd to be quite caſt down; and at the ſame time giving the Curate an Amorous Graſp by the Hand, ſhe pull'd him to her and made him write upon her Altar the Prophetic Terms he had made uſe of to let her underſtand the Fertility of her Arable Ground. After which ſhe thank'd him very civi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, telling him withal, that if all Men did but reſemble him in Piety and Natural ſtrength, Soldiers would not be ſo ſcarce in <hi>France</hi> as they were. <hi>I aſſure ye,</hi> ſaid the Princeſs, I <hi>was in a Diſconſolate Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition before you came; but you have given me as much Comfort as it is poſſible for me to receive. Perſons Sanctify'd to that degree as you are, have ſomething extraordinary a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove other Men. I muſt confeſs, I find 'em a thouſand times more engaging than your Court Minions who boaſt their fine Comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:135703:32"/>to the Ladies, but have no other Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit but that frivolous Excellency to commend 'em. Alas—Madam,</hi> reply'd Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur the Curate, <hi>with a great deal of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, we poor Abbots know not what Court<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip is; there is nothing in our Breviaries that tells us how to pleaſe Ladies. No mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> reply'd the <hi>Queen,</hi> with a paſſionate utterance, <hi>Nature that acts alone in you, is worth all the chiceſt and moſt Courtly Manner of forc'd Ability. In a word, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> cry'd out the Tranſported Lover, embracing the Knees of his Goddeſs, I <hi>may account my ſelf the moſt fortunate a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong men, ſince</hi> I <hi>ſee my ſelf ſo highly e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem'd by the moſt Adorable Queen in the VVorld. Let us have no Complaints, my Dear,</hi> reply'd the Princeſs, interrupt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him, her Eyes all ſparkling with Love, <hi>they are now quite out of ſeaſon. Let us make the beſt of the pretious minutes that are left us; let us looſe no time, but employ all in confirming to each other the mutual pledges of our Love.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The words were hardly out of her Mouth, when the Marchioneſs of <hi>P—s</hi> came to give her notice that King <hi>James</hi> was return'd out of <hi>Ireland</hi> and come to <hi>Paris,</hi> and that he was gone to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent of the Reverend Fathers the Jeſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>its.
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:135703:33"/>The Tydings caus'd the Sanctify'd Gallant forthwith to Decamp, who was afraid of nothing ſo much as to be taken Tardy in an Amorous Familiarity.</p>
            <p>King <hi>James,</hi> who was at his Wits end to ſee himſelf ſo courſly handled by Fortune, and hopeleſs of ever re-aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cending his Throne, was ſo caſt down, that nothing could comfort him. So that he was no ſooner arriv'd, but he ran firſt of all to the Jeſuits to tell the Lamentable ſtory of his Misfortune to Father <hi>La Chaiſe</hi> his faithful Friend. So ſoon as the Diſtreſſed Prince beheld the Reverend Father, he cry'd out in a Lamentable Tone. <hi>Ah—Father</hi> — I <hi>am loſt beyond Recovery;</hi> Ireland <hi>is totally re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd, and my Enemies are Victorious.</hi> The whole ſacred Society of Jeſuits, did all they could to chear up the poor Prince, who wept bitterly, and told 'em how King <hi>VVilliam</hi> had paſs'd the <hi>Boine</hi> and Routed his Army, and how he had afterwards made himſelf Maſter of <hi>Dro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gheda, Dundalk, Dublin, VVaterford</hi> and <hi>Duncannon—All's loſt,</hi> continu'd the King ſighing, <hi>every thing oppoſes my good Fortune, and my Stars ſhowre down their moſt Cruel Influencies uon me.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="63" facs="tcp:135703:33"/>
            <p>Upon this the Reverend Fathers <hi>La Chaiſe</hi> and <hi>Gerard</hi> carry'd King <hi>James</hi> to the <hi>Fauxburg St. Antoine,</hi> to the end they might diſpel ſome part of his grief, and buoy up his Heart with a plentiful Collation. Monſieur the Archbiſhop alſo no ſooner heard of his Arrival, but he went to wait upon him, making him a thouſand Offers of his Service, and tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling him, That his Majeſty might make uſe of his Purſe as his own, and that he would never forſake him.</p>
            <p>King <hi>James</hi> return'd his thanks with an extraordinary tendrneſs to the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor of the <hi>Sorbonne,</hi> aſſuring him that whatever kindneſs he did for him, ſhould be return'd him when it lay in his power. Thoſe laſt words caus'd the Archbiſhop to ſmile at the eaſineſs of that unfortunate Prince, who was the Cully and ſport of the World. This Opinion which the Archbiſhop had of the King, mov'd him to ſome pity, ſo that raiſing his Voice, <hi>Sir,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>be of good Courage, we ſhall find a way to ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour your Majeſty; ſettle your thoughts a little, and chear up your ſelf with us.</hi> With that they drank about ſeveral times King <hi>James</hi>'s Health, and to all his Friends that ſhould be inſtrumental to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:135703:34"/>his Reſtoration. After which they talk'd no more of Melancholy ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, but every one ſpoke of what was moſt divertiſing, and moſt proper to ſpend the time delightfully and merrily. At length King <hi>James</hi> perceiving it was ſomething late, took leave of the Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Fathers the Jeſuits; and the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop carry'd him to St. <hi>Germains</hi> in his Coach; which very much ſurprized the <hi>Queen,</hi> who could not conceive how they ſhould happen to meet together. The King being thus got Home, was receiv'd but very coldly by his Dome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticks. For they began already to look upon him as a King without a Crown, and as an Unfortunate perſon; which extreamly afflicted him. Our <hi>Monarch</hi> however diſſembl'd the Contempt which he had of his Couſin; conſidering it was more Generous rather then augment his Sorrows to divert his Mind with ſome Courtly Employment, to which King <hi>James</hi> at firſt was altogether averſe, but then reflecting that all his grieving and lamenting would not regain him his Scepter, nor the Dominion of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, he baniſh'd all his Diſturbances from his Thoughts for ſome time.</p>
            <pb n="65" facs="tcp:135703:34"/>
            <p>King <hi>James</hi> went often to Viſit <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam Maintenon</hi> at St. <hi>Cir</hi>'s, and made her the Confident of his thoughts, and of the Counſel which his Brother had given him to Court ſome pretty Lady, which made the <hi>Marchioneſs</hi> Laugh; however ſhe told him, That the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy was none of the worſt, and that Women were many times great helps to Men in this Life. <hi>Yes, Madam,</hi> anſwered King <hi>James, the pleaſure of Courting 'em is not to be parallell'd to thoſe that have a Contented Mind; but to a perſon in my Condition, Love is but an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nwelcome Gueſt.</hi> Upon this, the <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chioneſs,</hi> who found ſhe had a favoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Opportunity to revenge her ſelf upon her Rivaleſs and our Monarch, who had preferr'd the favour of King <hi>James</hi>'s Conſort before hers, and was very ſedulous in waiting upon that Princeſs, told King <hi>James,</hi> That if he were reſolv'd to undertake an Amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Heart, ſhe would provide him a Lady, with whom he might ſpend ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny a Charming Hour. <hi>Madam,</hi> ſaid he, I <hi>begin, methnks, to feel my imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſomewhat warm'd by the ſtory you have
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:135703:35"/>told me. But pray tell me, Madam, who this fair Lady is that you would have me male my Addreſſes to, in this ſorrowful Condition of mine. Sir,</hi> reply'd <hi>Madam de Maintenon, Nature muſt reinforce her ſelf, before you can think of any ſuch thing; the Buſineſs is not very preſſing; beſides that,</hi> I <hi>muſt have time to work the Mind and Heart of the Charming Lady that</hi> I <hi>purpoſe for your Embraces.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After this pleaſant Converſion, King <hi>James</hi> took his leave of the <hi>Marchio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> and return'd to St. <hi>Germains;</hi> where he was no ſooner Arriv'd, but Mrs. <hi>Laybady</hi> told him, That the <hi>Queen</hi> had had ſeveral Swooning Fits that Day, and that 'twas believ'd ſhe was with Child. To which the King anſwered ſomewhat unadviſedly, That it might well be ſo, but that he had been a long time Abſent. But Mrs. <hi>Labady</hi> was more diſcreet: For ſhe preſently withdrew without ſpeaking a word. However the Fainting Fits that ſtill diſturb'd the <hi>Queen,</hi> very much afflicted her petty Court. And the King, who diſſembl'd his Diſqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et, ſeldom ſtir'd from her. In a word
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:135703:35"/>the <hi>Queens</hi> Malady left her in a ſort time, and all the Phyſitians, after ſhe had conſulted them, concluded, <hi>That ſhe was big of two if not of three.</hi> A Midwife was alſo ſent for, who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm'd the ſame, which fill'd the whole Court with Joy, and <hi>France</hi> alſo, that had contributed ſo much towards it, would needs partake in the Happineſs of the two Princes, unfortunate in every thing elſe. The Venerable Council of <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIVth's Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, were overioy'd at it beyond the Expreſſion of Words. For this ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Off-ſpring rais'd the hopes of all the Jeſuitical Aſſembly. The Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend Father <hi>La Chasſe,</hi> and ſeveral of the Religious Orders, went to Congratulate the Queen upon her Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tility, and the Bleſſing that Heaven had ſent her. <hi>Oh—Madam,</hi> cry'd the Holy Father, <hi>Courage, you ſhall Aſcend your Throne once more, in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpite of all your Enemies. For</hi> I <hi>find that the Saints have heard our Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, particularly St.</hi> Vaubons, <hi>to whom</hi> I <hi>addreſſed a thouſand and a thouſand Vows, to the end her Girdle might work the ſame Effect upon you as it has wrought upon
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:135703:36"/>ſo many other Women that try'd the vertue of it. In truth Father,</hi> reply'd the <hi>Queen,</hi> I <hi>believe the Bleſſed Girdle of that Saint, to whom you paid your Vows, did me no harm. For</hi> I <hi>frequently made uſe of it, according to your Reverences Advice, with the uſual aſſiſtance that begets Mankind. In truth, Madam, your Majeſty has too much Knowledge, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that the Girdle of a Saint only, without the Company of a Man, can be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get a Child. Nevertheleſs, Father,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd the <hi>Queen, there are many poor Women, who are firmly of OPinion that they ſhall certainly be with Child by wearing that Bleſſed Girdle about their VVaſts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>As for your ſelf, Madam,</hi> reply'd the Father ſmiling, <hi>you are Cured of that Ridiculous Belief: VVhat a dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous thing would it be,</hi> continu'd the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>for Maids to touch St.</hi> Vaubon<hi>'s Robe, when the ſingle Ribbon which ſhe ty'd about her Loyns, being bound with Devotion about a Womans Waſt, could produce the Head of a Family.</hi> After this manner it is, that Pope <hi>Clement</hi> relates the ſtory in his laſt Book of the
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:135703:36"/>Life of that Saint. Thus it was that Father <hi>La Chaiſe</hi> let his Fancy ramble, when Monſieur the Archbiſhop, who had underſtood the welcome News as well as the reſt, came in. Every Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant of that Princeſs was extreamly pleas'd to underſtand that the <hi>Queen</hi> was big with Child; for thoſe Illuſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Lovers every one aſcrib'd to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves the Honour of the proſperous ſucceſs of their Labours. There was only the Duke of <hi>Vandome</hi> who ſwore the moſt ſeriouſly in the World, that he had never dipt his Pen in the Queen Inkhorn. Which became the Sport and Raillery of the Court. The <hi>Dauphin</hi> alſo Laught at it, ſaying, That 'twas a better Pen than any of the Doctors of the <hi>Sorbonne</hi> wrote withal; and that in time Fame would ſpread his Name far and near. The Princeſſes of <hi>Conti, Liſlebonne</hi> and <hi>Saiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons</hi> ſpo ted after the ſame man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. But that which ceas'd all theſe Railleries was a Pilgrimage which the Queen undertook, wherein King <hi>James</hi> was alſo to be concern'd to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with ſeveral other Devout Perſons. But he had earneſtly deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red his Beloved Conſort not to car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:135703:37"/>any Woman with her; for ſaid that pious Prince, <hi>Whereever they are there can be no Devotion. Henry</hi> III. obſerved the ſame Policy, when he walked bare-foot to carry his Offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings to any Saint. Wherefore His Majeſty was never Accompany'd up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thoſe occaſions, but by ſome of his Minions, clad like himſelf in White Linnen, and wearing large Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries, of which every Bead was car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved like a Deaths Head.</p>
            <p>King <hi>James</hi> being returned from his Pilgrimage, found himſelf fully Comforted for the Loſs of his Three Kingdoms. I know not whether his Converſation with St. <hi>Clotilde</hi> had o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ruled him wholly to ſubmit to the ſevere Decree of his Malignant ſtars, but there was a World of Joy obſerved to gliſſen in his Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance. About the ſame time it was, that being one day with the <hi>Marchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oneſs</hi> of <hi>Maintenon,</hi> the Lady ſtill deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to revenge her ſelf upon the Queen her Rivaleſs, took advantage of that lucky tender minute to Talk to him of the Affairs of his Heart;
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:135703:37"/>to which the King gave Anſwers ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry agreeable. Some days afterwards <hi>Madam de Maintenon</hi> ſent for <hi>Mde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moiſelle de</hi> — to her Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, who was the Fair Lady that ſhe deſign'd for the King and no King, a Lady at the ſame time tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly belov'd by our Great <hi>Monarch.</hi> So ſoon as King <hi>James</hi> ſaw her, he was Charm'd with her Beauty, and all the deſires of that poor Prince, that lay, as it were, in a Swoon, reviv'd at the ſight of ſo, Fair an Object; and his Fancy was heat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed after ſuch a manner, that he had much adoe to Recover him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf from an Agitation ſo extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary.</p>
            <p>But the Fair Lady, who could not brook with patience the feeble Careſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of that <hi>Prince,</hi> always contriv'd ſome excuſe or other, that ſhe might not meet His Majeſty; for as ſhe ſaid one day to the <hi>Dutcheſs</hi> of <hi>Nemours,</hi> I <hi>know not the meaning of Madam</hi> de Maintenon, <hi>to go about thus to Engage me to a Complyance with King</hi> James. <hi>One might think, as this Lady orders
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:135703:38"/>her Affairs, that the Race of Men were at an end. My dear Minion,</hi> reply'd the <hi>Dutcheſs</hi> with a ſmile, <hi>the Marchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oneſs of</hi> Maintenon <hi>has her Ends, and you muſt ſubmit to her.</hi> This An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer afforded nothing of Conſolation to our Charming Lady, who being at her Wits end to ſee her ſelf ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to Entertain a Familiar Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce with a Lover already come to his Spectacles, who had more need of Repoſe and Eaſe, then of the u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſual Agitations of <hi>Venus,</hi> reſolved to feign her ſelf ſick, that ſhe might rid her ſelf from the frequent Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſits of the King of the <hi>Baſs,</hi> and her project took. For the King be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing Enamour'd only by Accident, ſoon laid aſleep his Rapid motions in their proper places.</p>
            <p>However <hi>Madam Maintenon,</hi> who thought her ſelf in ſome meaſure Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venged, for the Inconſtancy of her Lover, and the Queen's interloping, was not a little glad that K. <hi>James</hi>'s A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour had made ſome noiſe at the Court; and tho the Conſequences were ſuch as ſhe expected and deſired, however ſhe would not ſeem to be diſatisfy'd.</p>
            <pb n="73" facs="tcp:135703:38"/>
            <p>The Queen who underſtood that 'twas the Marchioneſs of <hi>Maintenon,</hi> who had laid that Snare for her Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, only made here ſelf Sport with it, which nettl'd the Marchioneſs not a little. But the Queen who is infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely Witty and Politick withal, under ſtood ſo well how to manage both the Marchioneſs and our Monarch, that ſhe has all along to outward appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance preſerv'd her Friendſhip with thoſe Illuſtrious Perſons.</p>
            <p>All this while the Curate of Saint <hi>Martin,</hi> whom his Modeſty had kept ſilent, tho' he thought ne're a whit the leſs, imagin'd the time of his Abſence too long; and therefore ſo ſoon as the noiſe of the Queen's being With-child was quietly over, he went to St. <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains,</hi> under pretence of paying his Devoirs to King <hi>James,</hi> whom he had not ſeen ſince his Return out of <hi>Ireland.</hi> The Queen return'd him her Thanks, and in regard the King was not then at <hi>Paris,</hi> our two Lovers made the Beſt of his Lucky Abſence, by gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving each other a thouſand Proofs of their Affection. Our Princeſs made
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:135703:39"/>known to her Gallant her great Joy for being big With-child a ſecond time, in hopes that this laſt Infant would utterly overthrow all the Deſigns of the wretched <hi>Huguenots,</hi> who triumph'd over her Misfortune. Ah—my Dear, (continu'd the Princeſs, kiſſing her Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical <hi>Adonis</hi>) had King <hi>James</hi> undertaken an Affair of that Impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance as to beget a Child, the Poor Man would have been at a Loſs. You cannot imagine how uncapable that Prince is to beget his Like: So that the Marchioneſs of <hi>Maintenon</hi> miſtook in her Politicks to chooſe out a Miſtreſs for a Man that can hardly make Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: alas—poor Woman, ſhe thought to make me jealous, but ſhe took a wrong Courſe: I knew too well my Husband's Merits, and that there is ne're a Girl i'the Town, if ſhe be any thing handſome that will be baffl'd by ſuch a doating Gallant. But Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, (reply'd the Curate) I believe that Lady's Deſign was to fret and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiet your Majeſty, becauſe ſhe knows that our King has a great Eſteem and Honour for you, and uſually the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſes
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:135703:39"/>of Kings are jealous of their Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valeſſes. 'Tis a ſtrange thing (reply'd the Queen) that a Woman of her Age ſhould not be ſatiated with Love: yet you cannot imagin perhaps how amorous this Antiquated Bigoteſs is. After ſhe has turn'd about her Roſary an hour or two, the good Lady goes to careſs the King with a thouſand Grimaces, which no way ſuit with a Woman of her Character. In ſhort, ſhe loves Pleaſure better then her Life, and when ſhe cannot pleaſe her ſelf, ſhe produces others Younger and more Beautiful. This is the Genius of the Abbeſs of St. <hi>Cyr,</hi> notwithſtanding all her Devotion.</p>
            <p>In truth Madam, I never took that Lady to be ſo given to the World, or ſo addicted to Pleaſure. However ſhe ought to conſider that ſhe is in her wain, and that 'tis time for her to leave off. Ah! Monſieur — (reply'd the Princeſs) ſhe has been always a Wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton. A Friend of mine told me ſince I came to <hi>Paris,</hi> that when <hi>Scarron</hi> mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry'd her, every body told the Poor Man but of Charity, that he was going to
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:135703:40"/>ally himſelf to the Family of <hi>Acteon,</hi> To which the Growthead <hi>Aeſop</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd, that he laugh'd at wearing Horns, ſince he was not the only Man i'the World that did ſo, and that he only took that Fair Damſel to pleaſe his Eyes.</p>
            <p>But the Arrival of the Count of <hi>Lau. ſun,</hi> who ſurpriz'd the Queen, caus'd 'em to alter their Converſation: for now they talk'd of nothing but the Affairs of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and the loſs of <hi>Limerick.</hi> Ah! my dear Couſin, (cry'd the afflicted Princeſs) what think ye of my Mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune? I muſt confeſs, Madam, (reply'd the Count, rubbing his Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head) I am extreamly troubl'd for all theſe Misfortunes. There is nothing vexes a General more then to be foil'd in his Enterprizes. I wiſh I had never been in <hi>Ireland</hi> for my Honour's ſake. The Count of <hi>Tyrconnel</hi> and I did all that could be expected from ſtout Soldiers. But 'tis in vain to toil when Fortune is againſt us. You have given me a ſad Protraiture of our Condition, my dear Couſin, but I had thought that a great Soldier like your ſelf, had always re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:135703:40"/>ſome Hope: nevertheleſs, I ſee that—The Queen could not conclude the reſt, becauſe a Torrent of Tears that fell from her Eyes would not ſuffer her to proceed. Which the Count beholding, and ſorry to ſee her ſo terribly afflict her ſelf, he took her in his Arms to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort her, Swearing that he would try the to'ther Bout, and doe his Utmoſt to reſtore her Majeſty to her Throne.</p>
            <p>After the Queen had dry'd up her Tears, looking upon the Count with a tender Eye, My dear Couſin, (ſaid ſhe) how much am I oblig'd to your Kindneſs, for intereſting your ſelf ſo much in my Concerns. 'Twas you that ſav'd me out of the Hands of my Enemies, as well as the Prince of <hi>Wales</hi> my little Son. Now that I am big With-Child again, I have ſtill more need of your Aſſiſtance, to the end it may be publiſh'd to the World that this Great Belly of mine is no Fable, as they who bereav'd me of my Crown believ'd and gave out. O Heaven! that know'ſt the Injuſtice done me, proſecute my Revenge, and thou Saint <hi>Vaubons,</hi> who haſt given Life to the
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:135703:41"/>Infant which I bear, be thou for ever on my ſide. Prove but thou faithful to me, and I will burn upon thy Altar the largeſt Tapers I can buy for Money.</p>
            <p>The Count <hi>de Lauſun,</hi> who had heard that the Queen was VVith-child, Madam, (ſaid he to her with a Smile) I find that you have not been idle in my Abſence, and that Love has been your Friend. Oh — Couſin, (reply'd the Queen with a languiſhing Aire,) deride not an Unfortunate Princeſs that breathes nothing but Grief; this Production is only the Effect of my Prayers to St. <hi>Vaubons.</hi> Had yee no humane Aſſiſtance? Madam, (ſaid the Count, proceeding ſtill in his Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting Humour. None at all, (anſwer'd the Queen.) Then moſt certainly, (reply'd the Count) St. <hi>Vaubons</hi> muſt be a Hermophrodite to get Children a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone by her ſelf.</p>
            <p>You do not take the Bleſſings of Heaven in a right ſenſe, (reply'd the Queen): Let us find ſome other Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe. How did yee like the Iriſh Ladies, are they as handſom as they
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:135703:41"/>are at <hi>London?</hi> — How many Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſes had you, during your ſtay in that Country? Faith—Madam, I was ſo taken up with the VVar, that I had no leiſure to diſcern the VVhite from the Brown; beſides that I ſhould never court the Iriſh Ladies—they are ſo little obliging that they will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver make any great Conqueſts. Then you have been Viſiting 'em, Couſin, (reply'd the Queen, laughing) yet you would make me believe you never minded 'em. I know that <hi>Mars</hi> and <hi>Venus</hi> have a great Sympathy together. For which reaſon it is that <hi>Ovid</hi> ſhews us thoſe two Deities ſurpriz'd in an Amorous Familiarity, and fetter'd in ſmall Chains that <hi>Vulcan</hi> had Forg'd, to cure himſelf of his jealous Suſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions.</p>
            <p>The Count would have gone on with his Pleaſantries in anſwer to the Queen, when King <hi>James</hi> arriv'd. So that after ſome few Complements, the King and the Count went toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to the <hi>Fauxburgh</hi> St. <hi>Antoin,</hi> to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr with the Reverend Father <hi>La Chaiſe.</hi> At what time the Holy Father
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:135703:42"/>gave King <hi>James</hi> a Writing, the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents of which were as follows.</p>
            <p>
               <q>
                  <hi>Francis</hi> by the Grace of God, and the Holy Apoſtolick See, Archbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Paris,</hi> Duke and Peer of <hi>France,</hi> Commander of the King's Orders, Protector of the <hi>Sorbonne,</hi> and Superiour of that of <hi>Navarr,</hi> with the Aſſiſtance of our Venerable Brethren, Deans, Canons of the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tropolitan Church, and the Pious Council of <hi>Lewis</hi> the Great, our In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparable Monarch, moſt humbly ſupplicateth the King and Queen of <hi>Great Britain, James</hi> II. and <hi>Mary d' Eſte</hi> his Illuſtrious Conſort, to conſent to the means which we have found out in our Holy Aſſembly, ſpeedily to reſtore Their Majeſties to their Throne; which is, to publiſh a Declaration to their Engliſh Subjects, therein deſiring 'em not to join with King <hi>William,</hi> with Promiſe to obtain all their Privileges, and to give full Liberty to the Engliſh Religion, to ſend back all the Foreign Soldiers ſo ſoon as he ſhall be reſtor'd to his
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:135703:42"/>Throne: to let 'em ſee alſo that their manner of diſpoſſeſſing him, was unjuſt, by juſtifying his Conduct; deſiring alſo the Lords of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom to come to <hi>Paris</hi> to be preſent at the Delivery of the Queen, for the Diſſipating of all falſe Reports that ran about upon the Death of his Son, the Prince of <hi>Wales,</hi> and that the Queen's time expir'd the 15th. of <hi>May,</hi> aſſuring thoſe that ſhould come into <hi>France</hi> all the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty they could deſire.</q>
            </p>
            <p>The King and Queen return'd their Hearty Thanks to the Archbiſhop and all the Holy Society for the Good Counſel they had given. Prayers were alſo appointed to be made in all the Churches for the Bleſſing of Heaven upon all King <hi>James</hi>'s Enterprizes; and <hi>Te Deum</hi> was ſung before-hand, there being no Queſtion but that Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry would favour him.</p>
            <p>Some days after all this devout Hurly-burly, the Court remov'd to <hi>Marli,</hi> to divertiſe themſelves, where the Count <hi>Lauſun,</hi> always Courtly according
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:135703:43"/>to his Cuſtom, gave the moſt magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficent Regale that ever was ſeen. Balls and Comedies were not omitted for the Ladies to ſpend their time with plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and delight. The next day the Count carry'd the Queen, together with the Princeſſes of <hi>Conti, d' Eſpiney,</hi> and <hi>Soiſſons,</hi> to an <hi>Opera,</hi> where the Queen, who is a paſſionate Lover of Muſick, was charm'd with a young Damſel's Voice, who ſung the laſt Airs of <hi>Baptiſt.</hi> The Counteſs of <hi>Rourre,</hi> who was one of thoſe that went to <hi>Marli,</hi> was one of the firſt that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn'd, that ſhe might have more time to taſt the Sweets of her Engagement with the Prince of <hi>Turenne.</hi> At that time it was, that he was ſo weak as to Sign a little Note with his Blood to that ſame Charming Counteſs, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he promis'd to love her as long as he liv'd, and never to change. On the other ſide, Madam <hi>de Rourre</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear'd ſo charm'd with his Promiſe, that ſhe flung her ſelf about his Neck, and tenderly embrac'd him, telling him withal, That ſhe would be as faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to him as her Strength would per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit.
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:135703:43"/>For you know, my Dear, (con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinu'd the Cunning Coquet) that Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, ſuch as I am, are ſubject to ſtrange Temptations: Nevertheleſs, I aſſure yee, I will ſeparate my ſelf from the World, to the end I may give my ſelf up wholly to you. This was then the Opinion of the Fair Counteſs, who at the ſame time preſented her Illuſtrious Gallant with her Picture in a little Box, and ſeveral other Toys as Pledges of her Love. The Prince al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo Sign'd another Note with his blood, that ſhe ſhould never ſee the Picture again till the Hour of his Death, which fell out to be as he ſaid: for he was Slain at the Battel of <hi>Steen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kirk.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By this time the Queen being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver'd, infus'd a general Joy into all the Court for the Birth of a ſecond Child. Our Pious Monarch had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſir'd the Dutcheſs of <hi>Orleans</hi> his Siſter-in-Law to be God-mother. But by Misfortune that Princeſs who had a great Deſire to have been at the Queen's Labour, came too late, tho' ſhe ſet forth from St. <hi>Clou,</hi> with all ſpeed that might
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:135703:44"/>be. However every Body congratu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated King <hi>James</hi> for his good Fortune: and ſeveral Ladies of Great Quality always ſtay'd in the Queen's Chamber, by <hi>Lewis the Great</hi>'s Order, who ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly lov'd the Princeſs, and took de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in thinking that by his Tillage ſhe had produc'd ſo fair a Crop. And indeed this Infant was compos'd of ſeveral Eſſences; which in time will give it a moſt Admirable Odour in the World, and be a means to perpetuate his Memory. Monſieur the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop made frequent Viſits to the Queen, during her Lying-in, particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly to give her his Benediction, and make her ſome other Preſents of things neceſſary for the Support of Life. Telling her withall, to divertiſe her, That he had order'd to be car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry'd to his Country-Houſe, upon the Road from <hi>Charenton</hi> to <hi>Conflans,</hi> ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral ſorts of Liquor fit to be preſented to the Table of the Gods. Among the reſt a certain Brewage which the Archbiſhop had caus'd to be made at <hi>Paris;</hi> but I know not the Compoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. 'Tis ſufficient to let yee under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand,
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:135703:44"/>that the Queen and ſeveral other Ladies, ſometimes took a little too much of this Nectar, when they went to viſit our Apoſtolick; which caus'd 'em to ſleep very contentedly in the Arms of that Illuſtrious Gallant, who frequently lay'd aſide his Violet Caſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſock to put on the Habit of Madam Preſident <hi>Bretonvilliers,</hi> whom he had lov'd above all his Miſtreſſes to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. But in regard that Time is a Thing that cannot be ſtopp'd, Age had worn away the Allurements of that Fair Lady. Which was the Reaſon that Monſieur the Archbiſhop had a little neglected her for more Youthful Play-fellows, and which were better worth his Trouble. The Abbeſs of <hi>Monmatry</hi> alſo had the ſame Deſtiny, becauſe her Nuns that were in the Spring of their Years, far more delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully charm'd the Venerable Prelate. For which reaſon he had always ſome particular Benediction to beſtow up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thoſe Pious Damſels, who devout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly return'd him Thanks out of a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Motive of Gratitude.</p>
            <pb n="86" facs="tcp:135703:45"/>
            <p>The Report that was ſpread about <hi>Paris</hi> of the Deſcent that King <hi>William</hi> deſign'd to make into <hi>France,</hi> ſet all Tongues a talking of nothing ſo much as of ſetting forth a Great Fleet for King <hi>James.</hi> For which reaſon Four hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd Veſſels were ſtopp'd to carry Twelve thouſand Soldiers, as well Horſe as Foot, in defence of our Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunate Prince: and this Fleet was to be guarded by Twelve Men of War, under the Command of the Duke <hi>d' Eſtrees,</hi> who had 'em ready fitted out at <hi>Toulonne.</hi> In the mean time King <hi>James,</hi> who arriv'd at the <hi>Hogue</hi> the 29th. of <hi>April,</hi> began to embark his Men: but by reaſon of the Bad Weather which oppos'd his Deſigns, they prov'd abortive to his great Sorrow. Which oblig'd him to write a Letter to all the Engliſh Soldiers and Seamen, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he promis'd ſeveral Recompences, if they would be faithful to him, as alſo to maintain 'em in their Employments, with a great Number of Fair Words of the ſame Nature. But no body came to take his part, ſo that the poor Prince, unhappy in every thing he undertakes,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:135703:45"/>was conſtrain'd to return with Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miny to <hi>Paris,</hi> after he had waited a long time at <hi>La Hogue</hi> for a Wind, that would not blow him one King Blaſt, notwithſtanding all his Vows and Prayers to St. <hi>Barbe,</hi> who is the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector of the Seamen, when they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voutly recommend themſelves to him for Succour. I know not whether King <hi>James</hi> pray'd with a Faith ſtrong enough; but certain it is, the dogged Saint would by no means hearken to the Cries of his Suppliant at that time. This was a terrible Blow to the Court of <hi>France,</hi> and a Heart-breaking to the Pious Society of the Reverend Fathers of the Company of Jeſus. Every one in particular wiſh'd a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Miſchiefs to the <hi>Huguenots</hi> and their King: and the Jeſuitical Cabal plung'd in deſpair to ſee that Fortune turn'd her Back upon 'em, lay'd ſeveral Criminal Deſigns well known to all the World, which came to nothing. The Queen, who was got abroad a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, appear'd every where with a Penſive Countenance, and took no pleaſure in any thing. She was always
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:135703:46"/>at the Convent of Mercy in the <hi>Faux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh</hi> St. <hi>Germain,</hi> with Madam the Princeſs of <hi>Carignan</hi> a devout Old Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man that eat up her Saints Images with Kiſſing 'em, and wore out the Linea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of their Faces with continual rubbing and cleaning 'em. But the Queen, perceiving the Extraordinary Piety of this Reverend Piece of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity, could not long agree with her Humour. Thoſe Pleaſures to which our Princeſs was by Nature prone, return'd every Moment to her Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance; maugre all theſe Misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes, her Lovers were always wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come to her, and her deep Affection caus'd her to forget the Fatality of her Star. For which reaſon it was, that when our tenderly enamour'd Princeſs did not ſee her dear Curate, ſhe would ſay to her ſelf, that he knew not how to make his beſt Advantage of the moſt ſenſible Paſſion in the World; and that of all Pleaſures, that of being reciprocally belov'd was the ſweeteſt. Juſt at the time when the Queen was in this Trance, ſo favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable to Love it was, that <hi>Lewis the
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:135703:46"/>Great</hi> found her in her Cabinet leaning upon the Table, with her Eyes half ſhut, and in ſuch a Careleſs Dreſs as ſhew'd that the Amorous Careſſes of one of her Gallants would not have been diſpleaſing to her: ſo that our Monarch took his Advantage of the Shepherd's Hour, nor did the Queen oppoſe him but very weakly. All ſhe ſaid to him, giving him a wiſhful Look, was only this, Oh Sir, you wound me. In which part, Madam, (cry'd the King, altogether ſurpriz'd) I ſhould be mightily concern'd if any thing but Good ſhould befall yee by my means. 'Tis my Heart, dear Prince, which you have ſo ſenſibly touch'd, that makes me Sigh. I always touch Ladies (reply'd his Majeſty laughing) in the moſt ſenſible Parts.</p>
            <p>The Queen was about to ſpeak, when ſhe was in a ſtrange Surprize to ſee Madam <hi>de Maintenon</hi> come into her Chamber, the Door of which by Misfortune was left open. But if the Queen were ſurpriz'd, the Marchio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs was no leſs aſtoniſh'd to ſee the King lying upon the Queen's Bed by
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:135703:47"/>her ſide, and that in none of the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſteſt Poſtures neither, which made her ſtart two Steps backward. <hi>Sancta Maria,</hi> cry'd our Abbeſs, (lifting up her Eyes to Heaven) what Sight is this I ſee! Oh Sir, Human Frailty always over-rules you, and you will never be wiſe for your Health—You know the wrong you do that little ſtrength that is left yee by making Attempts beyond your Power. The King who lay ſtill upon the Bed, not being able to recover himſelf from the Surprize he was in to hear the Reproaches of the Marchioneſs, which at the ſame time diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover'd to the Queen his Majeſty's in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ability to undertake the Combates of Love, at length anſwer'd the Marchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oneſs very rudely, That ſhe was too bold to reprove him like a Child; that he was King and able to govern him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf—and then looking upon her with a Frown of Contempt—Be gone (ſaid he) you will extreamly oblige me. Upon which Madam <hi>de Mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non</hi> made a low Curt'ſie, and retir'd out of the Room. The Queen who feign'd her ſelf aſleep all this while, and
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:135703:47"/>as if ſhe had heard nothing before her Rivaleſs, ſo ſoon as ſhe was gone, I am loſt for ever, (ſaid ſhe to the King) this Lady has diſcover'd our Famili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arity, and ſhe will ruin my Reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion if ſhe can. She dares not (re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd the King) ſhe is too great a Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litician to prefer the Pleaſure of her Revenge before her Fortune in this World: reſt your ſelf content for that: I am Maſter of my own Will, and I will love whom I pleaſe. In the mean time Sir, (reply'd the Princeſs) I am deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly concern'd for one thing. How could this jealous Woman divine that Your Majeſty was here? I muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs indeed that Love has a Piercing Eye, when it lodges in the Heart of an Old Woman, and who is not only concern'd, but jealous to the higheſt degree. Talk no more of it (ſaid our Monarch, embracing his divine Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs) all will go well.</p>
            <p>So ſoon as the King had taken his leave of the Queen, he return'd to <hi>Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſailles,</hi> where he was a long time with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſeeing Madam <hi>de Maintenon,</hi> who kept her Station at St. <hi>Cyr,</hi> during her
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:135703:48"/>Exile, not being able to recover her ſelf from the harſh Expreſſions which the King had made uſe of to let her underſtand how much he was diſpleas'd. But at length, having conſider'd the Condition of her Affairs, and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſities of her Heart, Oh—(ſaid ſhe to her ſelf) how weak is a Woman when ſhe is in Love! but yet the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt of a King is a Precious Thing which any prudent Woman would ſtudy to preſerve. Immediately there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhe went to the King, who was then alone in his Chamber, and walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in a melancholy poſture. Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently the Marchioneſs threw her ſelf at his Knees and begg'd his Pardon. The King, who is the greateſt Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tier living, could not endure to ſee a Woman, whom he had vehemently lov'd, ſo ſubmiſſive at his Feet; ſo that he took her by the Hand and rais'd her up, ſaying to her no more then this; I am convinc'd of your Sincerity; but be more diſcreet for the future. Oh—Sir, (reply'd Madam <hi>de Maintenon</hi>) I am guilty, becauſe it is your Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty's Pleaſure I ſhould be ſo. 'Tis true
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:135703:48"/>that I oppos'd your Pleaſures, but it was becauſe I was too zealous for your Good, that I have brought upon me your Diſpleaſure. But the King, who was unwilling to rip up old Stories, fell upon other Diſcourſe, and asked her what News of the Princeſs of <hi>Conti</hi> whom he had not ſeen for ſome Days.</p>
            <p>The Marchioneſs, after ſhe had gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven a full Account of what he deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from her, return'd to St. <hi>Cyr;</hi> where ſhe was no ſooner arriv'd, but King <hi>James,</hi> who was quite tyr'd out with muſing upon his Misfortunes, came to give her a Viſit. Nor was Madam <hi>de Maintenon</hi> at all diſturb'd to ſee him. For in regard ſhe had a Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret Intrigue with him, ſhe made no Scruple to tell him the whole Story of the King, and the Queen his Wife; which very much ſurpriz'd King <hi>James.</hi> But after the Marchioneſs had entruſted him with this Secret, and made him underſtand the Danger of making a Noiſe of it, which was not convenient for a Hunder'd Reaſons of Policy, Sir, (ſaid ſhe to him) diſſemble
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:135703:49"/>the Wrong your Wife do's yee, and Revenge your ſelf by paying her in the ſame Coin. You acknowledg'd to me, That the laſt Engagement you had, would have diverted yee with a thouſand Pleaſures, if the Fair Lady that you lov'd would but have anſwer'd your Paſſion: but there is no always ill Succeſs in the Fortune of Love; there is ſometimes a Calm in <hi>Cupid</hi>'s Empire, as there is Peace and Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quillity in other Dominions of the World. I have one of my Girls which I intend to diſcard, becauſe ſhe begins to be a little wantonly enclin'd, and for that ſhe is too eaſie in her Love of Men, which is not proper for Saint <hi>Cyr,</hi> where we muſt have nothing but Good Inſtructions and Good Examples for the Youth that are under my Care. It may be ſaid in Praiſe of this Damſel, tho' ſhe have this failing, that ſhe is one of the moſt amiable Girls in the World. She has lovely Eyes well en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chas'd, an Admirable Complexion, a little Mouth, Teeth whiter then Ivory, her Neck well built, and a Curious Shape; ſhe is neither too tall nor too
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:135703:49"/>ſhort: in a Word, ſhe has all to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie the moſt curious Eye. For which reaſon the Count of St. <hi>Manre</hi> always call'd her his Delight; nor do I believe that the Dauphin hates her; which is a Thing I cannot ſuffer; for I do not like it, that he ſhould thruſt his Noſe into my Buſineſs; beſides that we have not been Cater-Couſins ever ſince I ſaid, that the Princeſs of <hi>Turenne</hi> and the Counteſs of <hi>Rourre</hi> were a couple of Coquets.</p>
            <p>Well, Madam, (ſaid the King, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupting her) if I ſhould addreſs my ſelf to the Lady you ſpeak of, what likelyhood of Succeſs for me, ſince thoſe brisker Sparks enjoy her. Oh—Sir, you go too faſt, they have not had the handling of her yet; for I verily believe this pretty Girl has her Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denhead ſtill, tho' to her Sorrow. You will oblige me therefore to crop thoſe early Flowers. For by that means ſhall I revenge my ſelf of the Queen your Wife, and upon the Dauphin, who begins to reliſh Kiſſing of Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
            <pb n="96" facs="tcp:135703:50"/>
            <p>I am of your Opinion, (reply'd the King, laughing) I believe he will become more gentle and civiliz'd among the Ladies. Come, come, (reply'd the Mardchioneſs) I believe him as ſenſible of Love as other Men, only he loves Privacy in his Amours, he do's not publiſh 'em by Sound of Trumpet in the City, like <hi>Lewis the Great,</hi> when he makes any new Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery. I remember when he was a Young Man, and in Love with the Tapſtry Weaver's Daughter of <hi>Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſailles,</hi> and the Fair <hi>Madelon Denis,</hi> who was alſo the Daughter of a Well-digger of the ſame Place, he never car'd that any Body ſhould know he went to viſit his Miſtreſſes, and if any Body that knew him, ſurpriz'd him in their Houſes, he was gone preſently, making as if he only came to look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their Work. I believe, Madam, all that you ſay of the Dauphin, (re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd the King) but 'tis true that the Count of St. <hi>Maure</hi> frequently viſits Mademoiſelle <hi>de Broiſy,</hi> our Charming Picardin. That's nothing, Sir, there is no Danger, (reply'd the Marchio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:135703:50"/>that Spark of <hi>Venus</hi> never viſits her but by Night; his Amour is No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cturnal, of the ſame Nature as the wooing of Cats, that Court one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther upon the Tiles by the light of the Moon; provided you make your Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſits in the Day-time, you will never be interrupted with the ſight of him. For this ſame pretty Minion of the Dau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phin's obſerves all his Methods. The King of <hi>Albion</hi> having quitted Madam <hi>de Maintenon,</hi> went the next day, after he had ſpruc'd himſelf up, to ſee Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demoiſelle <hi>de Broiſy,</hi> who had left the Marquis's Convent and liv'd with an old Aunt of hers in the <hi>Fauxburgh</hi> Saint <hi>Honorè.</hi> So ſoon as the Young Damſel ſaw King <hi>James,</hi> ſhe fell a laughing — Sir, ſaid ſhe—what brings you hither? Surely Madam <hi>de Maintenon</hi> muſt have intruded upon your Civility to make you thus the Meſſenger to deliver her Errands. Not ſo, Fair One, (reply'd the King) 'tis only my Deſire to kiſs your Hands, that makes me pay you this Viſit. Sir, (ſaid Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demoiſelle <hi>de Broiſy</hi>) I am infinitely oblig'd to you for the Honour which
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:135703:51"/>you do me. After ſome Comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, King <hi>James</hi> would fain have been Careſſing her, after the Manner of the Court of <hi>France,</hi> where they never make any tender Proteſtations to Ladies, but preſently go to the point—which not a little ſurpriz'd the Lady, who ask'd him what he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to be at?—nothing but the ſweet Game of Kiſſing, my Dear Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nioneſs, (reply'd the King) if you pleaſe. Oh Sir, (reply'd the Young Lady) there are ſo many Kiſſers i'the World now adays, that they put me out of Conceit with Love — Recall your wandring Affections home again, and ceaſe to tire your ſelf with Luſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Deſires, which may warm your Imagination, but otherwiſe expoſe you to Vexation and Sorrow. Such a dry Anſwer put King <hi>James</hi> into ſuch a diſorder, that he had not a Word to ſay for himſelf. And the Charming Picardin, obſerving how ſhe had ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenc'd the Poor King, left him with a Smile of Deriſion, and ſaid no more to him.</p>
            <pb n="99" facs="tcp:135703:51"/>
            <p>King <hi>James,</hi> who was troubl'd at the Ill Succeſs of his Amour, made a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful recital of it to the Marchioneſs of <hi>Maintenon,</hi> who upbraided him that he had neither the Means nor the Art to win a Lady's Affection, which were two things very neceſſary for a Man, and alſo very pleaſing. The Prince made Anſwer, That however, he ſtrook the Ladies in the moſt tender part, and took the moſt proper way to warm 'em. But continu'd he with a Sigh, Love is no more favourable to me then Fortune; thoſe two Deities are my declar'd Enemies, tho' I never offended 'em. Madam <hi>de Maintenon</hi> put an end to the Diſcourſe by asking the King, whether he would go along with her who was going to viſit one of her ſhe Friends, and ſo they took Coach together.</p>
            <p>The Prince of <hi>Turenne,</hi> whom we left with the Counteſs <hi>de Rourre,</hi> find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Time drawing near that he was to go to the Army, made frequent Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſits to his dear Miſtreſs, as if ſome fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bodings of Death had hinted to him that he ſhould never ſee her again.
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:135703:52"/>And this was that which he told her every day, as ſhe ſate upon his Knee. Ha! my Dear, my Adorable, I ſhall never return more, my Mind and ſomething within me tells me ſo. Yet all the Reluctancy I have to leave the World is only for thy ſake. And ſo ſaying, he could not forbear dropping ſome few Tears, which the Counteſs wip'd away, fondling him with a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Careſſes—Why ſhould you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain ſuch mournful Thoughts, my dear Prince, (ſaid ſhe) I hope your Better Fortune will bring you back again. 'Tis not that which ſo much diſturbs me, but that which makes my Life happy, your Amiable Preſence will be eclips'd for ſome time from me. How difficult a thing it is to keep thoſe Bleſſings which we moſt delight in.</p>
            <p>The Prince of <hi>Turenne</hi> who ſaw her ſomewhat dejeced by what he had ſaid, took her in his Arms to comfort her. Never did Lovers give each other greater Proofs of mutual Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction then they two did; the Days were too ſhort for 'em to taſte the Sweets of Love; and therefore they
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:135703:52"/>ſpent whole Nights together without being tir'd, which rarely happens in Amorous Combats. But our Charm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Counteſs is generally indefatigable in the Sports of <hi>Venus;</hi> the more ſhe taſtes, the more greedy ſhe is. For which important Reaſon it was, that ſhe always entertain'd a Croud of Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers that were ready to ſerve her in their turns. Nor do I ſpeak this with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out good Ground. For ſo ſoon as the Prince of <hi>Turenne</hi> had left her, and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven her a thouſand Aſſurances of his Fidelity, ſome few Hours after, the Dauphin, who came to viſit her, ſpent the remainder of the Day and the next Night with her.</p>
            <p>Her Inconſtancy and fickle Humour is well known at Court, and the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of <hi>Conti</hi> was in the Right When ſhe upbraided the Prince of <hi>Turenne</hi> for his want of Niceneſs in adhering ſo ſtedfaſtly to a Woman that was ſo prodigal of her Favours to all Comers and Goers, and who many times un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſonably meets 'em half way. The Princeſs of <hi>Turenne</hi> is not a Woman of this Character; for ſhe never cares to
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:135703:53"/>peſter her ſelf with many Sighers at a time; and 'tis ſaid that ſhe never lov'd any Body ſo tenderly as the Dauphin who had not the ſame Sentiments for her. What a folly 'tis for a Lady to love by her ſelf? In a Man that weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is to be pardon'd, becauſe he is more capable of Love then Women, who ought always to be the laſt and much more Circumſpect in ſetting their Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections: for nothing is more dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous then to embark in an Amour. Alas! 'tis a common thing to Ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrack in the Port of Hope, when we think our ſelves in ſafety: the ſureſt way therefore is to love but ſlightly, and without Vehemency of Attach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. What probability is there (ſaid the Fugitive Queen ſome time ſince to the Princeſs of <hi>Conti,</hi> who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn'd Violent Paſſions) for a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man to preſerve her Heart for Indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rency, which is the Winter of Love. Oh, Madam, (reply'd the Queen ſinging the following Lines,
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:135703:53"/>
               <q>
                  <l>When Tenderneſs moves, in vain we pretend</l>
                  <l>To ſay where the tender Engagement will end;</l>
                  <l>When firſt an Amour is but newly begun,</l>
                  <l>'Tis unknown what 'twill coſt us at the long run.</l>
                  <l>Alas! for my Heart, it had ſtill retain'd Its Primitive Innocence,</l>
                  <l>Had it growing Deſire quite baniſh'd from thence</l>
                  <l>And a Stranger to Love remain'd.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis true, (continu'd the Queen) an En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement ſometimes coſt us very dear; but how ſhall we paſs away our Youth without a little Love. That Paſſion is all the Pleaſure of Life; and the Days ſeem long without a little Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment for the Heart, which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightfully ſpends our time. Monſieur the Archbiſhop, who overheard all the Ladies diſcourſe at the Door, fell into a loud Laughter, which made the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of <hi>Conti</hi> riſe from her Seat to ſee who was there; but ſhe was ſtrangely ſurpriz'd when ſhe beheld the Illuſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:135703:54"/>Prelate. Thereupon they chang'd their Subject, and fell to talk of Piety; which the Queen did onpurpoſe, to the end they might not ſuſpect her Intrigue with the Roman Doctor; but 'twas in vain for her to play the Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrite; for her wiſtful Looks de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clar'd the Contrary. Beſides that the Princeſs of <hi>Conti</hi> has too quick a Wit, to be ignorant of the Queen of <hi>Qlbion</hi>'s Gallantries. The Queen alſo her ſelf obſerv'd that there was an Eye upon her; which made her leave the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany ſooner then otherwiſe ſhe would have done; then which there could have been nothing more favourable to the ſanctify'd Prelate, who deſir'd above all things an Opportunity to make known to her Majeſty the Exceſs of his Love. The Queen, who ſtill diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembl'd at her uſual rate, feign'd that all the Careſſes of her Lover were moſt acceptable to her, and that ſhe preferr'd 'em before all others; which greatly aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented the Prelate's Delight, belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving himſelf the moſt fortunate of Men, in poſſeſſing the Heart of ſo amiable a Princeſs entirely to himſelf. But Men
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:135703:54"/>are frequently deceiv'd in their Hopes, particularly about Matters of Love, which promiſes more Felicity then it has in ſtore, and fills the Thoughts of thoſe that Love with a thouſand airy Bleſſings. Thus it was that Monſieur the Archbiſhop flatter'd his Paſſion, in careſſing the Queen, who aſſur'd him on her part, That ſhe would be faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to him as long as ſhe liv'd, and that ſhe could never love any other but him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, for Reaſons that her Majeſty could not expreſs.</p>
            <p>All theſe tender Proteſtations being at an end, the Archbiſhop took his leave of the Queen, and went with his Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficial to meet the Biſhop of <hi>Meaux</hi> at the Houſe of one of the Preſidents, who liv'd at <hi>Liſle Notredam.</hi> After he had diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cours'd of Publick Affairs, and of the Decrees which our Monarch had iſſu'd forth, the two Prelates went to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>create themſelves at <hi>Conflans</hi> about a ſmall League from <hi>Paris,</hi> where they drank ſo much of the Archbiſhop's good Wine, that it warm'd the devout Friends of <hi>Bacchus</hi> to that degree, as to tell what Favours they had receiv'd
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:135703:55"/>from their Miſtreſſes, which put them upon relating ſeveral pleaſant Stories that held 'em a long time. The Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Meaux</hi> drank the Queen's Health ſmiling upon the Archbiſhop, who pledg'd the Company very cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſly, telling 'em withal, That no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing was more acceptable to him, then to hear 'em talk of that Princeſs, in whom he had obſerv'd an Extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Merit, and that Fortune was not juſt to abandon her Cauſe. What you ſay is true Sir, (ſaid the Preſident) but we are not alway rewarded ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to our Deſerts; wherefore your Artiſts paint that Deity Blind. Upon that, the Biſhop of <hi>Meaux</hi> could not forbear deſiring his Friends to drink a good Health to the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop's Inclinations, naming no Body. But in regard the Conqueſts that Love makes, can be no more conceal'd then Fire it ſelf, every Body knew that Fair Ladies took up the greateſt part of that Illuſtrious Prelate's time. The Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident, laughing at the ſame time, ſaid that Madam <hi>de Bourneville</hi> had a great Share in the Joy that appear'd in the
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:135703:55"/>Biſhop of <hi>Meaux</hi>'s Countenance. Nor did that Prelate much gainſay it; quite the contrary, with a Courtly Aire he confeſs'd that he was as ſenſible of the Charms of handſome Ladies as another Man, and that his Character could not mortifie his Paſſions, and that the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibitions of the Church forbidding Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimony, and the touching any Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, did but corroborate the Propen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of Men to that Sex. Every Body applauded the Biſhop's Opinion, which was maintain'd for Truth by ſeveral Glaſſes of Wine which they drank off, and then threw over their Shoulders in honour of the Ladies. Never was ſo much Incenſe offer'd to <hi>Bacchus</hi> and <hi>Venus</hi> as that Day, which ſeem'd to be one of their Feſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vals. After this Debauch was at an end, which laſted a day or two, the Pious Fathers of the Roman Catholick Church return'd to <hi>Paris</hi> more ſerious then ever.</p>
            <p>King <hi>James</hi> whom the bad Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of his Affairs had caſt into a deep Melancholly, and who knew not how to imploy himſelf to diſſipate his Trouble, and to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:135703:56"/>the mournful Idea's that crouded his Thoughts for the Loſs of his Crown; ſpent his time in a thouſand Trifles. Amongſt the reſt, he very frequently went to ſee his Son, the Little Prince of <hi>Wales,</hi> to dandle him, and hear his Prittle-prattle, which was very Extra-ordinary, conſidering his Years. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demoiſelle <hi>de Bordage,</hi> a French Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, who was plac'd about him to teach him the Language, and to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern him in the Abſence of his Tutor, always made a faithful Relation of the hopeful Parts of the Young Prince, which made the King often laugh at her manner of Expreſſing her ſelf. But as it is impoſſible to avoid loving handſome Perſons, nor to let 'em un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand as much, King <hi>James</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd to make a Tryal of his Skill, maugre his unwillingneſs to do it. For the Poor Prince had ſo ill ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded in his Amours, as well as in every thing elſe, that he durſt not at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt the making of tender and amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Declarations. Nevertheleſs the Poſture of his Affairs requir'd it, to the end he might diſpell the Troubles
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:135703:56"/>of his Mind, as we have ſaid al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready.</p>
            <p>One day, this ſolitary Prince ſaid ſighing to Madam <hi>Bordage,</hi> That he was the moſt unfortunate of Men in all his Undertakings, and that he never proſper'd in any thing, which reduc'd him ſometimes to that Deſpair, that Death it ſelf would have been wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come to him. And indeed the King had no great Reaſon to take any Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in this Life; for every Body look'd upon him with Contempt ſince his Fatal Fall. Mrs. <hi>Bordage</hi> ſeem'd to be compaſſionately mov'd with the King's bemoaning his Affliction to her; ſo that ſhe endeavour'd to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort him up the beſt ſhe could. VVherein King <hi>James</hi> obſerv'd a great deal of good Nature, and thank'd her for her being ſo much concern'd in his Troubles. His Majeſty ſpent ſome time in Acknowledgment which grw up to Love, and which he kept ſecret in his Heart, without ſpeaking a Word for above ſix Months. But in regard that Paſſion cannot laſt long without burſting forth, the King, who
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:135703:57"/>was troubl'd with concealing it longer, reſolv'd to ſpeak of it to her that had given it Birth and Growth: but ſtil in dubious and far-fetch'd Expreſſions, only to ſound the Ladies Intentions. The Fair Lady, who thought the King was talking to her of ſome Advantage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Match, ſhew'd her ſelf nothing Squeamiſh in her Anſwers. Which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm'd our Amorous Prince in his Hopes. For which reaſon, he urg'd her one day to tell him, Whether ſhe could tenderly Love an Honeſt Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man who ſhould think himſelf happy to pleaſe her. Sir, (ſaid ſhe) I know not what to ſay, you puzzle me with your Propoſal, for I would willingly ſee the Perſon you propound. You know, Sir, (continu'd ſhe) that we muſt have a Sight of the Objects be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we fix our Love, that we may have ſome Foundation for our Paſſion. 'Tis very certain, Madam, (reply'd King <hi>James</hi>) but true Lovers are ſtill afraid of being favourably heard; and therefore they are not ſo forward to declare themſelves at firſt. If this Perſon you ſpeak of, Sir, be a Perſon
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:135703:57"/>of Merit, for any thing elſe, you need not fear his being belov'd. That Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit of Madam <hi>Bordage</hi>'s made the King laugh, who reply'd, I find, Madam, that you love handſome Young Men that have a great Deal of Wit. Yes, Sir, (anſwer'd ſhe) I have always had a Kindneſs for deſerving Gentlemen. The King, perceiving this Lady would never love a Perſon who had ſo little to recommend him as he had, ſhe ath'd up his Comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, without ſaying any more, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the reſt to Fortune; tho' there is no great likelyhood that ſhe will ever be kind to that miſerable Prince.</p>
            <p>The Curate of St. <hi>Martin,</hi> who had not ſeen his divine Queen in ſome time, went to the Convent of <hi>Mercy</hi> to vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit one of his Kinſwomen, with a deſign to meet the Queen there, who frequently went to viſit the Princeſſes of <hi>Soiſſons,</hi> both Priſoners in that place. But ſo ſoon as the Curate ſaw her Majeſty, he chang'd Colour, and ſeem'd to be abaſh'd, which the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany well obſerv'd, tho' they thought him only daſh'd out of Countenance
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:135703:58"/>by the Queen's Preſence. But they were quite other Motions which caus'd that Diſturbance in our Illuſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Gallant. His Love for that Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs put him ſometimes into ſtrange Diſorders, which however he took great Care to conceal. But the Queen, who was not ſo ſcrupulous, chid him frequently for ſo doing, tho' he begg'd her ſtill to diſſemble their Intrigue as much as ſhe could.</p>
            <p>After they had been for ſome time at the Convent, and talk'd of ſeveral Pleaſant and Witty Things, the Queen took her leave of the ſorrowful Siſters, and went to take a Promenade in her Coach with the Curate of St. <hi>Martin,</hi> as alſo to make two or three Viſits, which by no means pleas'd the Abbot, who lov'd privacy in Sinning, and who would have lik'd it much better to have been Head to Head with his Princeſs in her Chamber. However Good Manners would not permit him to leave her, and there was no other way but Patience; for he muſt follow all the Dances the Queen led him.</p>
            <p>At length the Sun beginning to Set,
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:135703:58"/>oblig'd the Queen to return to Saint <hi>Germains</hi> with her Lover, who was weary of running from Viſit to Viſit, and ſeem'd to be glad of a little Soli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude with his dear Miſtreſs. The Queen therefore deſiring him to walk up into her Chamber, lay down upon the Bed with her Soul-ſaving Curate by her, who ſeveral times aſſur'd her of his Love, and his Tenderneſs for her Majeſty. To which the Queen em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bracing him, made anſwer, That ſhe ſhould have a perpetual Love for him, and that ſhe would never change her Inclination. And their Converſation was ſtill upon the ſame Subject, when Madam <hi>Bordage</hi> was ſent to give the Queen notice that Supper was read. With that our Lovers ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what heated with their Amorous Dal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liances, took time to cool themſelves before they went down. The Curate alſo would fain have been going home, but the Queen deſir'd him to Sup with her; to which, with much ado He conſented. For the poor Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate was always out of Order when he had been careſſing the Princeſs;
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:135703:59"/>which put him into a kind of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion when he came into Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany.</p>
            <p>The Queen obſerving his Weakneſs, upbraided him before ſhe left the Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber. What! (ſaid ſhe) my Dear, ſuch a Novice to be thus out of Heart upon a little Amorous Combat! you will never make a true Soldier of <hi>Venus,</hi> if you have not more Courage and more Reſolution. Come, come, (ſaid the Queen, taking him by the Arm) the Meat is upon the Table, and Supper will grow cold; two or three Glaſſes of Wine will revive your Strength, and put yee ino a better Humour. That ſaid, the Curate could not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear laughing at the ſprightly Gaiety of the Queen. However all the Supper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time, not a Word of any thing but Piety and Devotion, which the Italian Ladies always obſerve to do, when they are with their Gallants, to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuade the World that they have been doing no Harm, and that their Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liarity goes not ſo far as Courtſhip, which requires great Caution. But for all that, they may give Credit to
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:135703:59"/>outward Appearances that pleaſe; we muſt needs ſay that the Fugitive Queen leaves nothing omitted to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertiſe her ſelf, and to forget her Mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunes which would every day pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to her Eyes a thouſand dreadful Idea's, did ſhe not take care to remove 'em from her ſight.</p>
            <p>After they had Supp'd, the Queen retir'd to her Chamber, where ſhe play'd at Cards for an Hour or two with her Gallant, who knew the King <hi>James</hi> was abroad, and that he would not return home by ſuch a Time. Their Diſcourſe all the while was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly Pleaſant and Jocular, and a thouſand pleaſant Things were diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cours'd of to paſs away the time. The Curate was never in ſuch a brisk Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour as at that Inſtant, his Eyes ſparkling with an Amorous Fire, and the moſt tender in the World, which extreamly pleas'd his Princeſs, who was not wanting on her part to ſupply the Converſation with a thouſand Fancies and Witty Jokes that naturally flow'd from her, for which reaſon ſhe is
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:135703:60"/>tenderly belov'd by thoſe that are inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate with her.</p>
            <p>And now the Night being far ſpent, the Curate took his leave, after ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Adieu's, intermix'd with moſt paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionate and ſenſible Aſſurances. For the Queen who was weary of Saint <hi>Germains,</hi> has made a Match with a Lady of her Intimate Acquaintance to ſpend two or three Months with her at her Houſe about ſix Leagues from <hi>Paris.</hi> Which was the Reaſon that our two Lovers had much ado to part; and tho' the moſt tender Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtations were made uſe of, they could not forbear letting fall Tears in abundance, particularly the Curate, whoſe Soul was very ſenſible of the Abſence of his Beloved, and who ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd the loſs of her with an Impati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Grief. As for the Queen, ſhe was more eaſily rid of her Sorrow, having a large and ſpacious Heart, which was the Reaſon that her Melancholy had the more room; beſides that ſhe lov'd ſeveral Perſons at a time, which divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded her ſeveral ways, and freed her
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:135703:60"/>from any vehement Attachment. And now the Day for her departure being come, the Queen went to take her leave of her Friends, not forgetting the Archbiſhop to whom ſhe pay'd a Viſit, under pretence of conſulting with him about Important Affairs, which infus'd an extraordinary Joy into the Prelate, who ſplendidly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal'd his Princeſs. Mean while, the Dutcheſs of <hi>Nemours,</hi> and the Marchio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of <hi>Seignelay,</hi> who were of the Knot, waited at her Home with great Impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, for it was high time to be gone. But the Queen, who was well at eaſe with her enamour'd Piece of Gravity, never thought of her Company; which conſtrain'd the Marchioneſs to ſend one of her Pages to let the Queen un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand that the Marchioneſs ſtay'd for her. With that the Queen took her leave of her enamour'd Father <hi>Grizzle,</hi> who waited on her in his long Violet Robe to her Coach, tenderly Kiſſing her Hand at parting.</p>
            <p>So ſoon as the Ladies ſaw the Queen, Wemuſt confeſs, Madam, (ſaid they with a Smile) that Religious Perſons
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:135703:61"/>have a great Aſcendant over your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, and you are ſo paſſionately in Love with the Fathers of the Church, that 'tis a trouble to yee to leave their Company. 'tis true indeed, Ladies, that the Archbiſhop is the moſt Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaiſant Perſon in the World. He wants neither Diſcourſe nor Pleaſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries to entertain his Gueſts. Nothing leſs, Madam, then our Archbiſhop's Talents can merit your Eeſtem (re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd the Dutcheſs of <hi>Nemours.</hi>) But let us loſe no time—we have a long Journey to Ride. Thereupon the Queen and the reſt of the Company, took Coach and left the Town, to the great Grief of their Lovers.</p>
            <p>The next Day the Queen being arriv'd at <hi>Lily</hi> with her ſmall Court, Hunting-Matches, Banquets, and a thouſand other Country Divertiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, afforded every Day new Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies of Pleaſure. But in regard that Mirth is never perfect without the Maſculine Sex, the Ladies, when they ſaw two or three Cavaliers of their Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance that came to viſit 'em, their Pleaſures redoubl'd in ſeeing the
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:135703:61"/>Lords, who correſponded to the Beſt of their Power with the Ladies Civi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities. Among the reſt, there was the Chevalier <hi>de Soiſſons,</hi> who fell in Love with the Queen's good Humour and her Wit, which ſhe can wind and turn to Sport and Merriment as ſhe pleaſes. I admire how this Princeſs could har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour ſo much Jocundry, conſidering her Adverſities, which would have caſt any other but her ſelf into an Abyſs of Grief, and caus'd her for ever to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce the World. Yet thoſe mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Idea's make no Impreſſion upon her Majeſty. On the other ſide, the more our Italian is oppreſs'd with Calamity, the more ſhe addicts her ſelf to her Delights.</p>
            <p>The Chevalier <hi>de Soiſſons,</hi> who left nothing omitted to ſecond the Inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his Princeſs, ſupply'd her with all the moſt Charming Pleaſures he could invent; and becauſe he knew ſhe was a Paſſionate Lover of Muſick, and of whatever was grateful to the Sences, he entertain'd her with the moſt Harmonious Simphonies in the World of all ſorts of Inſtruments in
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:135703:62"/>the middle of a Forreſt; after which, there was a Magnificent Collation rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy prepar'd under a Shady Bower: All which Divertiſements would have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly pleas'd the Queen, had they coſt her nothing. But the Chevalier who never did ſomething for nothing, but expected that the Favours of the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs ſhould reimburſe him for his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pences, never left her, perceiving in her Phyſiognomy that ſhe was none of the cruelleſt, and that ſhe lov'd the Company of Men. Wherein he was not deceiv'd, ſeeing it was the Queen's weak ſide. She has alſo ſeveral times confeſs'd, that Love was the thing to which ſhe was moſt enclin'd, and which charm'd her above any thing in the World. For which reaſon, Men that admir'd the Female Sex were always welcome to her. But as for thi laſt Gallant, the Princeſs had other meaſures to take. For the Chevalier <hi>de Soiſſons</hi> was the Archbiſhop's Intimate Crony and his Confident. That Prelate entruſted this Young Spark with all his Secrets, becauſe he was the moſt diſcreet and faithful of all that he had honour'd with his Friendſhip.</p>
            <pb n="121" facs="tcp:135703:62"/>
            <p>All theſe Conſiderations kept the Queen's Mind in ſuſpence: ſhe knew not what to do, to ſatisfie her new Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, who every day gave her a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Proofs of his Affection, and who could not live a Minute abſented from her. How ſhall I dare to truſt a Young Man, (ſaid ſhe to her ſelf) who it may be after he has receiv'd all the Favours I can beſtow upon him, will make it his delight to boaſt of 'em pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly in the City, as all Perſons of his Age commonly do, which would be an Extraordinary Trouble to me, particularly if the Archbiſhop ſhould know it. How would that Prelate be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpatter me with the Reproaches of Faithleſs and Perfidious, after ſo many Oaths and Aſſurances, as I have given him! No Darling of <hi>Venus,</hi> that ſollicit me to Infidelity, flatter me no more with your new Charms, ſince my Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty oppoſes your Pleaſures. Thus the Queen argu'd with her ſelf at ſome times, and at others was e'en ready to ſurrender to him the moſt precious Jewel ſhe had, not being able to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the Importunate Charms of her
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:135703:63"/>Victor. At length, one day that this Princeſs was alone with the Chevalier, and that ſhe felt her Heart very tender, and not able to reſilt a Violent Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, ſhe would have gone away from him. But the Chevalier ſtopp'd her, tenderly asking her the Reaſons why ſhe fled him. I know not, (re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd the Queen, with a troubl'd Countenance) I feel my ſelf ſo feeble and haunted with an Idea which per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexes me, that I cannot tell how to expreſs it to yee. Ah! Madam, (cry'd the Chevalier, who knew what it was that troubl'd the Princeſs) would I might be ſo happy as to be able to allevi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate your Pains, and leſſen your Sorrows. Oh, Sir, (reply'd the Queen with a mournful Tone) your Preſence do's but aggravate 'em—how troubleſome a thing it is to Love—She ſtopp'd at this laſt Word, which ſhe utter'd notwithſtanding the Oppoſition of her Tongue. Her Heart no longer able to diſſemble, ſpoke in deſpite of her Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luctancy, as uſually it happens to Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that would diſguize their Love. But the Chevalier who would not be put off
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:135703:63"/>with theſe little Shilly-ſhally Tricks, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hrew himſelf preſently at her Feet, and Kiſſing her Hands a thouſand times, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>wore to her, That he lov'd her better <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hen himſelf, and that he ſhould be the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oſt unfortunate of Men if ſhe had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ot Compaſſion upon him in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ition wherein he was. The Princeſs, who was as much Embarraſs'd as her Gallant, ſaid the ſame thing to him. Never was ſeen an Amour ſo languiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or which rais'd more Pity: To <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ell yee what they did to comfort them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, I will not undertake, becauſe I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>now nothing but that the next Eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing it was obſerv'd that the Queen <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>as very Penſive and full of Medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on, which the Ladies took notice <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f by way of Raillery; telling her, That ſhe had ſome Reaſons for quitting <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eir Company, for that as far they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ould underſtand, the Advantage of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e Promenade had redounded to her, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd they had only far'd the better for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er Company. The Queen made no an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>wer to this and a thouſand other Petty <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aillieries that were thrown upon Her <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d the Chevalier, who appear'd well
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:135703:64"/>ſatisfy'd with his Good Fortune, and never regarded what they ſaid. The Dutcheſs of <hi>Nemours</hi> could not chooſe but fall a Laughing to ſee the Queen ſit ſo gravely and ſoberly, who ſpoke very little at all that Evening, feigning her ſelf not well.</p>
            <p>The next Morning the Princeſs, who had reflected upon every thing that paſs'd the Day before, found her ſelf a little more Blithe and Gay. It ſeems the Night which is the Counſellor of all Men, had given her new Vigour and Joy. Which pleas'd the Chevalier, who was troubl'd that his Love had occaſion'd her Sadneſs. After this, they went to walk in the Garden to take the Air; at what time the Queen, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving towards a Fountain to behold the Figures that compaſs'd it, and ſpouted Forth Water into ſeveral parts of the Garden, gave the Chevalier an Oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity to ſtop likewiſe, and to declare to his Fair Queen the Condition of his Heart in the moſt Paſſionate Terms that might be, asking withal how ſhe had paſs'd away the Night. Sadly e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, (anſwer'd ſhe with a Sigh) I
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:135703:64"/>am afraid my Weakneſs for your ſake will do me an Injury. How! Madam, (reply'd the Chevalier) can you mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſt the Fidelity of my Love? After the kind Favours I have receiv'd from your Majeſty, I ſhould be the moſt wretched of Mortals, ſhould I betray the moſt amiable Princeſs that ever was. Theſe Aſſurances pacify'd the Queen's Diſturbances, and caus'd her to return to <hi>Paris</hi> with a full Tranquil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of Mind, not dreaming that her Young Gallant would have ſo indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creetly publiſh'd the Favours he had receiv'd at her Hands.</p>
            <p>However the firſt thing he did when he ſaw the Archbiſhop, was to tell him the whole Story as it had been acted, and that the Queen was very Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table. Why ſay you ſo, Sir, (reply'd the Prelate ſmiling) no Body can have too much Compaſſion for the Miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable. 'Tis very true, Sir, (anſwer'd the Chevalier <hi>de Soiſſons,</hi> laughing out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right) true Charity has no Bounds. The Prelate, in a few Words unfolded the Young Chevalier's Enigma, and immediately went and told it to the
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:135703:65"/>Queen, who was at her Wits end to find her ſelf ſo baſely betray'd. This is your hare-brain'd Fop, (ſaid ſhe to the Sorbonne Doctor) that you value ſo highly, who is ſo impertinent to tell the Greateſt Lyes in the World: his Indiſcretion deſerves Puniſhment, a Bruit not worthy the Conſideration of ſuch a Perſon as I am. But I ſhall tell him his own. This ſaid, the Queen went into her Cloſet, and in the Heat of her Anger wrote the following Lines.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>The Queen's Letter to the Count of <hi>Soiſſons.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THings are reported in the World that no Body could know but your ſelf and I; but I am aſſur'd I never publiſh'd 'em; and this will be eaſily believ'd, if you conſider the Nature of the Things that are divulg'd. This vile Report proceeds then only from your Indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion. Nevertheleſs you have the Impudence to make me the Object of your Raillieries, and to give it out
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:135703:65"/>
                     <hi>That I am very Charitable.</hi> Perfidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Man! not content to violate the Oath of Secreſie which you ſwore to me, but perhaps daring enough to make me Falſe Proteſtations of your Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit Innocency. But I know yee now; and you ſhall never triumph more over my Tenderneſs; I am re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover'd from my Error, and find you altogether unworthy to enjoy the leaſt Kindneſs of ſuch a Princeſs as I am. A Man cannot be indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creet without being perfidious, as I am fure you are. For which reaſon I can no longer love yee; my Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon teaches me, that Men love only out of Vanity, and that they act not out of any Principle of Honour. I am oblig'd to your Infidelity for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo well inſtructed. Adieu, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidious Man. Nothing vexes me ſo much, but that I was ſo baſely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luded by a Traytor.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>I cannot expreſs the Surprize that ſeiz'd the Chevalier, when he had read this Letter, He that thought to have diverted himſelf with his Good For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune.
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:135703:66"/>He preſently judg'd it could only come from the Archbiſhop his good Friend. But in regard that Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vals can never agree, the Prelate who was jealous to the higheſt pitch, could not endure that any Body ſhould ſpeak reproachfully of the Perſon that he lov'd above all others. For that reaſon he preferr'd the Princeſs's Amity before the Chevalier's Friendſhip, who did but laugh at the Buſineſs, and made a hunder'd Jeſts and Railleries upon it. Among the reſt this was one of his Lampoons, ſpeaking in the Perſon of the Woman.</p>
            <q>
               <l>When we our Favours grant, in Love's hot Fury,</l>
               <l>Men muſt Diſcretion uſe,</l>
               <l>And in th' Eternal Grave of Silence bury,</l>
               <l>What we perhaps could not refuſe:</l>
               <l>Diſcloſe not the Secrets of Female Deſire,</l>
               <l>'Tis all the Reward that we Women require.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Theſe Verſes did but provoke the Queen, who after her new Gallant had carry'd himſelf ſo indiſcreetly,
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:135703:66"/>would no longer ſee any Body familiarly, finding 'em unworthy of her Favours, ſince they had not the power to keep the Secret, which is the main Act in Gallantry, that a Chevalier ought to obſerve. For Ladies, whoſe Inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions leads 'em to favour their Gallants, are mad when they meet with Infide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity. Theſe are the Important Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons why the Queen ſees no body that belongs to the Court. She now re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves all her Tenderneſs for the Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Orders, and the Fathers of the Society of Jeſus, who are not ſo gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally ſubjects to Human Frailties as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. Theſe Reverend Fathers have one Perfection which is not to be met with among ſecular Courtiers. They dare not publiſh the Favours they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive from Women, out of a Maxim which is hereditary to their Order. You ſee by this, what good Reaſon our Princeſs had to confine her Love with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Cloyſters. This is the way to have no more occaſion of repenting for having condeſcended to the fickle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Chevaliers, who cannot ſometimes forbear to ſet upon the
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:135703:67"/>Wings of Fame the Kindneſſes which they receive from their Miſtreſſes.</p>
            <p>However the Queen, after ſhe had for ſome time taken up a Reſolution to ſee no Body, began to be weary of it, when Monſieur the Curate came to viſit her. The Princeſs was very glad to ſee him, and was extream<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Civil, giving him an account of her Troubles, and of the Diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction which ſhe made between Him and Others. The Curate far from contradicting her, agreed with her in what ſhe ſaid, and convinc'd her, that there were no Men i'the World that better underſtood how to preſerve a Secret then the Church-men. What you ſay is very true, (anſwer'd the Princeſs) for which reaſon, I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce all the Gallantries of the Court, that I may wholly devote my ſelf to you without any Reſervation, as a thing that is very neceſſary; for I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſhake off the Inſtigations of my Heart; the time ſeems tedious to me, when I have not ſomething to Love. I confeſs, Madam, (reply'd the Abbot) that there is no Sweetneſs in Life with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:135703:67"/>a little Love; for the pleaſure of Loving is that which ſeaſons all things. Yes, my Dear, (reply'd the Queen, embracing him) I know there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that lives which can forbear Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving. The moſt Innocent of Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures make it appear by their tender Careſſes. All Nature loves, and there is nothing created but for Pleaſure. Oh, Madam, (cry'd the Curate) how I am Charm'd, that you concur with me in my Sentiments; Let us endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to unite our ſelves ſo cloſely toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that time which wears out the faſteſt Ligaments may never ſeparate us. You ſtretch to Immortality, Mr. Abbot (reply'd the Queen, laughing) you know that we cannot live always, and conſequently our Love muſt have an end; but let us Enjoy the Preſent time as much as lies in our Power. The Queen pronounc'd thoſe Words with an Aire the moſt amorous i'the World, which incited her Gallant to puſh the Opportunity forward. So that his En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amour'd Lady throwing her ſelf ſaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon a little Bed made after the Italian Faſhion, there is no queſtion to be made but that the Curate and his
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:135703:68"/>Princeſs taſted all the Sweets of their tender Affection. Our Lovers were in the midſt of their Dalliances, when Word was brought 'em, that King <hi>James</hi> was coming up Stairs. I leave you to gueſs how the Young Abbot was diſturb'd at this unexpected News. In ſhort, the Queen caus'd him to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume his firſt ſerious Countenance, and his Cloak, and his Prayer-Book in his Hand, making as if he had been ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dying his Breviary for the Edification of our Princeſs, who is extreamly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vout, as your may perceive by her Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Conduct.</p>
            <p>The King was overjoy'd to find his Conſort ſo piouſly employ'd. He careſs'd her with a world of tender Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, and was mighty thankful to the Prieſt, who acted the Hypocrite and the Saint the beſt that he could. The whole Converſation rowl'd upon Piety and Morality. Never had the Queen ſo great a deſire to have laugh'd out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right to ſee in what an unlucky Figure ſhe had made the poor Unfortunate Husband appear in, who is the moſt eaſie Man in the World, for he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves whatever is ſaid to him with
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:135703:68"/>the greateſt readineſs imaginable.</p>
            <p>By this, it growing near Dinner-time, the King invited the Curate, who very modeſtly excus'd himſelf, telling his Majeſty, That he had Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs of Importance that call'd him home, and which he could not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence withall; but that he was infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely oblig'd to his Majeſty for the Honour which he did him. Come, Mr. Curate, (ſaid the Queen, inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupting him) you want ſuch a world of intreaty—Come, come, the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer's a good Offer, and not to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fus'd. oh, Madam, (anſwer'd the Curate) 'tis my Misfortune, that 'tis not in my Power to enjoy this Offer, but I hope your Majeſty will not take it amiſs. After ſeveral other Complements, the Queen perceiving that her Invitation did but render her Gallant uneaſie, gave him his Liberty, letting him know however by a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Sign, that ſhe would be glad to ſee him oftner.</p>
            <p>The Abbot, being thus diſingag'd from King <hi>James</hi>'s Preſence, was the moſt overjoy'd Man i'the World, and went home to ponder upon the Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:135703:69"/>which he had receiv'd from his Incomparable Princeſs. Theſe Idea's infus'd a kind of Pride and Vanity in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, which his Acquaintance took notice of. For which reaſon his Siſter Madam <hi>de Fontaine</hi> upbraided him, that he was grown ſo haughty ever ſince his Admiſſion into St. <hi>James</hi>'s, that no Body was good enough to keep him Company. You will not always be the Favourite of a Queen, Brother, (ſaid ſhe) the good Fortune that comes from Great People, is as brittle as Glaſs, which the leaſt fall breaks in pieces. Oh—my dear Siſter (reply'd the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate) I can never believe, there will be a ſpeedy end of the Careſſes of that Princeſs. Truly Brother (an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer'd his Siſter) you are a Man of an Eaſie Belief, to think that you are the only Man that enjoys the Queen's Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours; ſhe loves all the Hats and Caps ſhe ſees; her Love knows no Bounds. The laſt Adventure ſhe had with the Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valier <hi>de Soiſſons</hi> is no ſmall Stain to her Honour, for that ſame Lord makes Sport with it to her diſcredit. If you knew how they talk of her at the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chioneſs of <hi>Seignelays,</hi> you would not
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:135703:69"/>have ſo great a Love and Eſteem for her as you have. But Siſter (anſwer'd the Curate) do you believe all that is ſaid; every body has the Liberty to Chat what they pleaſe. The Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chioneſs lies no leſs under the laſh of Scandal then the Queen. Many times People report a hunder'd Things of which they know nothing at all, telling a thouſand Tales only to paſs away the Time. Beſides, the greateſt People are not exempt from the Tongues of Scandal and Calumny. A Man muſt ſet himſelf above ſuch Trifles, if he intends to live at Eaſe. Mrs. <hi>Fontaine</hi> who perceiv'd that her Brother was reſolv'd to go his own way, left him, and went to viſit the Marchioneſs <hi>de P — s</hi> who was much her Friend out of a Motive of Intereſt, for that the Marchioneſs having a Paſſionate Love for Madam <hi>Fontaine,</hi> told her every thing ſhe knew. By which means ſhe came to underſtand a good part of her Brother's Buſineſs with the Queen, for that the Marchioneſs was every Day with that ſame Amorous Princeſs, and was the Depoſitory of her Secrets.</p>
            <p>The Marchioneſs and Madam <hi>Fon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine</hi>
               <pb n="136" facs="tcp:135703:70"/>being thus got together, had a long Chat together in Engliſh, all upon the Subject of the Queen's Gallantries, and upon the tender Expreſſions of the Queen, when ſhe is with her dear Curate Little doſt thou know, my dear, (ſaid the Marchioneſs) how hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py thy Brother is; the Queen kiſſes and embraces him a thouſand times aday, and talks to him a hunder'd pret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty things, the moſt endearing in the World. How came yee too know theſe Circumſtances ſo particularly, Madam, (ſaid Madam <hi>de Fontaine</hi> laughing) I know theſe things, my Dear, (ſaid the Marchioneſs) becauſe I often find 'em together billing like two Pigeons. Oh! cry'd Mademoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelle <hi>de Fontaine,</hi> Has my Brother puſh'd his Fortune ſo far? 'Tis very well, Mr. Abbot (continu'd ſhe) I find you are not always at your Books and your Prayers, and that your Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation is not altogether ſo Godly as you would make me believe. He were a Fool (reply'd the Marchioneſs) if he did not make the Beſt of the Oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity which his kind Stars preſent him. In Sincerity, my dear Child, thy Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:135703:70"/>has a Phyſiognomy that ſhews him no hater of Ladies, and therefore his Character and Function no way ſuit with him; beſides, doſt thou believe he would refuſe the Favours which ſhe beſtows upon him; no, no—he has more Wit then ſo. While the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chioneſs was thus talking, the Queen enter'd the Chamber, and ask'd her if ſhe would go along with her to pay a viſit to the Dutcheſs of <hi>Orleans.</hi> Now Madam <hi>P—s</hi> lov'd to accompany the Queen to the Dutcheſs of <hi>Orleans,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſhe would ſometimes ſay, when ſhe was in a good Humour, that ſhe admir'd that Prince for his Courtly ways above any other Perſon of the Court, which often made the Queen laugh, who was particularly acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with Monſieur the Duke, and would many times ſay that he had too Effeminate an Aire, and was too poor Spirited for a Prince of the Blood. But for all this the Marchioneſs would be continually ſpeaking in his Praiſe; and it was obſerv'd that her Paſſion grew ſtronger and ſtronger. So that the Queen ſaid to her, laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, one Day, Ah! my Dear, talk no
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:135703:71"/>more of thy Inclination; when thou wer't Young, perhaps the Duke might have had ſome Tenderneſs for thee; but alas! now, who would mind thee. 'Tis a ſad thing when a Woman comes to the Winter of her Age. The Marchioneſs ſeem'd ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing mortify'd by the Queen's Rail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lery, but modeſtly reply'd, 'Tis true, Madam, what you ſay; however you muſt acknowledge that Ages do's not deſtroy the Paſſions: Or if it make ſome alteration in our Complexions, yet ſtill we are ſenſible of ſome Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainders of what we have been. All this while (reply'd the Queen) I am not arriv'd as yet at your Years, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever I begin already to diſguſt the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliarity and Courtſhip of the World. When I conſider, my Dear, (conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nu'd the Queen) how little Men in general deſerve the Affection of Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, thoſe Idea's ſet me at an Incredible Enmity with that Inconſtant and Fickle Sex, who for the moſt part only act by Motives of Vanity, or by ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Principle of as little Value. No, no—Men love not now, nor did they ever Love. I have had ſeveral
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:135703:71"/>Woful Experiences of it. I find Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirement a thouſand times more charm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: the Pleaſures of Sence make thoſe Impreſſions that grieve and perplex the Mind; whereas the Delights of So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude are more ſweet and not ſo liable to Vexations. But Madam, (reply'd the Marchioneſs) is it poſſible for us to ſpend our Days always in Contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation and Silence? Somewhat of Motion in Life cauſes all the Sweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of it. I have ſaid the ſame thing as often as thee, my Dear; but I find by Experience, (anſwer'd the Queen) that the Motion which charms Thee, is ſometimes very dangerous, and that it produces ſtrange Effects. This Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation was interrupted by the Count of <hi>Lauſun,</hi> who ſtay'd a long time with the Queen to divert her with Variety of Stories.</p>
            <p>But let us return to the Viſit which the Queen gave the Dutcheſs of <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leans,</hi> where ſhe found a Croud of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of the Higheſt Quality. They fell to Play all the Afternoon, and then to the Comedy, which happen'd to be new and very Witty. But all theſe Paſtimes could not diſſipate the Queen's
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:135703:72"/>Diſturbances. Her Thoughts were taken up with the Faithleſsneſs of her Gallants, and the Reſolutions ſhe was taking never more to liſten to the ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Sentiments of her Heart. She was making an Agreement with her Eyes never more to be ſenſible of the deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Merits of her Adorers. Poſſeſs'd with theſe Idea's therefore, the Queen retir'd home with a world of Coldneſs and Indifferency, which extreamly ſurpriz'd the Company, who knew her brisk and airy Humour: every one argu'd after their own Fancies, and what their Thoughts ſuggeſted. Only the Duke of <hi>Orleans</hi> and Madam <hi>Maintenon</hi> hit upon the true Cauſe, and publickly declar'd that her Majeſty was reſolv'd no longer to keep Company with Men, becauſe ſhe did not find 'em faithful. Wo is me, (reply'd the Princeſs of <hi>Conti</hi>) how long has the Queen been troubl'd with this Qualm of Vertuous Sentiments? She was angry with me not long ſince, becauſe I laugh'd, and ſaid, that Gallantry was always attended with unlucky Conſequences. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, (reply'd the Duke of <hi>Vendoſm,</hi> ſmiling) when Women ceaſe to have
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:135703:72"/>a winning way, and become the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt of the firſt that comes, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoves 'em often to excuſe their Weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes; but if Women were wiſe that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire a Gallant, they would never change when they have the Good Fortune to meet with one that is diſcreet: but hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Frailty is ſo prevalent in us, that we want Ragoo's to whet our Appetites. The Duke utter'd theſe Words with an Aire the moſt Satyrical in the World. Which the Dutcheſs of <hi>Orleans</hi> having obſerv'd, Pray tell me, Sir, (ſaid ſhe) are you al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways ſatisfy'd with one Miſtreſs? and have you never any deſire to change? No, Madam, (reply'd the Duke) were I ſo hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py to enjoy one, I would no more leave her then the Shadow do's the Body. Ah! Good Man, (cry'd the Dutcheſs) what Pity 'tis, that ſo faithful a Lover as you ſhould want a Miſtreſs. How happy are you, (continu'd her Royal Highneſs) that you are in Love with nothing but Honour. Oh! Madam, (reply'd the Princeſs of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti</hi>) if I may be thought to know, what Monſieur the Dauphin told me t'other Day, this Diſſembler is embark'd in a very conſiderable Engagement. 'Tis Madam <hi>de St. Agrement</hi> who has now recover'd
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:135703:73"/>his Appetite; he is all on Fire for that Fair Lady. The Duke bluſh'd to hear the Princeſs declare ſo openly without any Reſervation, and with a ſerious Tone, Madam, (ſaid he) where had you all this News? 'tis more then I know my ſelf. The Princeſs upon that, perceiving that ſhe had diſguſted the Duke, turn'd the Diſcourſe another way. But Monſieur <hi>de Vendoſme</hi> could not for all that, forbear to manifeſt his Reſentment to the Princeſs, in forbearing to wait upon her as he was wont to do. The next Day the Dauphin reprimanded him; to whom the Duke reply'd with a ſerious Aire, I entruſted you with the Secret of my Soul, and you go and tell it again to a Lady who has much ado to conceal her own Privacies. I muſt needs tell yee, Sir, it very much troubl'd me, and that was the reaſon I did not wait upon her. Nothing vexes me more then an Amour diſclos'd. On the other ſide, if Madam St. <hi>Agremont</hi> ſhould come to underſtand that there was the leaſt ſuſpicion of her being gallanted, I muſt never ſee her more; which would be the greateſt Torment to me in the World, for I am paſſionately Enamour'd. I may ſay, without any Hyberbole, that ſhe is
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:135703:73"/>the moſt amiable Perſon that ever was born. Forbear to praiſe your Miſtreſs, (ſai the Dauphin) before Perſons that may fall in Love with her as well as your ſelf: Love enters into the Heart as well through the Ears as through the Eyes.</p>
            <p>Oh, Monſieur, (reply'd the Duke of <hi>Vndoſme</hi>) you are ſo taken up with your Illuſtrious Miſtreſſes, that you have not a Minute to ſpare to caſt your Eyes upon others. Be not over confident, (reply'd the Monſieur) Appearances are deceitful; I love Change as well as you: Adieu, I muſt leave yee for a Moment. Thus the Monſieur left the Duke of <hi>Vendoſme,</hi> and went to ſee the Counteſs of <hi>Rourre,</hi> whom he had promis'd to meet at an appointed Rendezvous.</p>
            <p>Let us now return to the Queen, who has now no longer any Inclination to the Gallants of the Court, or if ſhe has, 'tis ſo indifferent, that ſhe hardly feels her ſelf warm'd by it. She is now fully reſolv'd to obſerve the devout Leſſons which the Church-men inſpire into heer, and which ſhe finds more pleaſing to her Palate, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that this Devotion being well order'd, encloſes within it, unknown Myſteries that cover all Appearances of Pleaſure
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:135703:74"/>and Wantonneſs. The Convent of <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy,</hi> in the <hi>Fauxburg</hi> St. <hi>Germains,</hi> is the Uſual Place where the Queen now goes to ſay her Prayers in the Day-time with the Curate of St. <hi>Martin,</hi> who accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies her in her Pious Exerciſe, and who Preaches ſometimes in terms ſo full of Piety, that his Hearers muſt be inſenſible not to be mov'd with his Religious Orato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. 'Tis by that means, (ſaid the Queen) that this diſcreet Prelate has found the way to my Heart: Devotion enchants me beyond all things in the World.</p>
            <p>Thus you ſee what are now the Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Sentiments of the Fugitive Queen: we ought to believe that her Heart is ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere, and that ſhe is too generous to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guize it. Nevertheleſs, together with this Devotion ſhe cannot avoid reſerving ſtill, ſo far as I can find, ſome ſpare Hours to enjoy the Sweets of a ſanctify'd Amour; by vertue of which, the one half of her Sins is pardon'd, when they are only committed with the Fathers of the Church, who exte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuate the Crimes by their ſecret and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Morals. I ſhall conclude, deſiring the Reader to believe me, as one that is pretty well Convinc'd of the Truth which I have deliver'd.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:135703:74"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:135703:75"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:135703:75" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
